<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>المجلة العلمية للدراسات التجارية والبيئية</title>
    <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/</link>
    <description>المجلة العلمية للدراسات التجارية والبيئية</description>
    <atom:link href="" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <language>ar</language>
    <sy:updatePeriod>daily</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>قياس أثر تطور مقومات العوامل التنافسية الصناعية علي إنتاجية العاملين بقطاع الآثاث المصري للفترة من (2008- 2019 )</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279751.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;إستهدفت الدراسة الحالية التعرف علي أثر تطور العوامل التنافسية للصناعة علي إنتاجية العاملين بقطاع صناعة الأثاث المصري عن الفترة من 2008 حتى 2019 . وبناء عليه تضمنت العوامل التنافسية للصناعة أربعة أبعاد متمثلة في (حجم العاملين بالصناعة؛ حجم الشركات الصناعية؛ قيمة إجمالي الإنتاج؛ الأجور النقدية للعاملين) إعتمدت الدراسة علي التحليل الوصفى وكذلك التحليل القياسي مستهدفة بذلك تفسير العلاقات بين المتغيرات المستقلة والمتغير التابع.وتوصلت نتائج الدراسة إلي أنه يوجد تأثير للعوامل التنافسية للصناعة بأبعادها المختلفة علي إنتاجية العاملين بصناعة الأثاث.وفى ضوء نتائج الدراسة، أًقترِحَتْ الباحثة بعض التوصيات التي تسعى إلي المساهمة في حل بعض المشكلات المرتبطة بكل من: الصناعة وكذلك الموارد البشرية التي تعمل في إطارها بهدف زيادة الإنتاجية وتحقيق المزايا التنافسية للصناعة المصرية.&amp;amp;nbsp;The study aimed to identify the impact of the development of competitive factors for the industry, on the productivity of workers in the Egyptian furniture industry for the period 2008 to 2019. The competitive factors of the industry include four dimensions: (the size of workers in the industry; the size of industrial companies; the value of total production; the wages of workers.The results showed that there is an impact of the competitive factors of the industry in its various dimensions on the productivity of workers in the furniture industry.In light of this, there are some recommendations to solve the problems and obstacles related to the industry and workers in order to increase productivity and achieve competitive advantages for the Egyptian industry.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر التسويق الوردى على القرار الشرائى ... دراسة ميدانيه</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279752.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث&amp;amp;nbsp; الى معرفه أثر&amp;amp;nbsp; الدور الذى يلعبه التسويق الوردى بعناصرة ( المنتج &amp;amp;ndash; السعر &amp;amp;ndash; الترويج&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;ndash; التوزيع&amp;amp;nbsp; ) فى مراحل اتخاذ القرار الشرائى للمرأه المصريه&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; ، وكذلك معرف أثر العوامل الديمغرافيه ( العمر &amp;amp;ndash; الدخل &amp;amp;ndash; الحاله الاجتماعيه- مستوى التعليم) فى العلاقة بين التسويق الوردى وقرار المرأه المصرية&amp;amp;nbsp; (قبل &amp;amp;ndash; أثناء- بعد ) لشراء للملابس الجاهزة.ومن أهم النتائج التي توصل إليها البحث : ضروره عمل الورش والندوات التعريفيه لفهم ايجابيات وسلبيات التسويق الوردى لغير المتخصصين ، وتركيز جهود المسوقين فى قطاع الملابس على فهم حاجات ورغبات المرأه ومحاوله تجزئه القطاعات السوقيه وفقا لمعاير الديمغرافيه.وأوصى الباحث بعدة توصيات أهمها: ضرورة أهتمام قطاع الملابس خصوصا وباقى القطاعات عموما بالتسويق الوردى عند التخطيط التسويقى ، يجب على اى مؤسسه تستهدف شريحه النساء ان لا تهمل الجانب الترويجى فى الوصول الى ثقه وولاء المرأه لذلك يجب تشجيع المشاريع والمؤسسات العامه على تطبيق منهج التسويق الوردى ، الاهتمام بأخذ التغذيه الراجعه والأراء والاقتراحات و الافكار من النساء اللاتى يترددون بشكل دائم للتسويق فى المجتمعات التجاريه.The research aims to find out the impact of the role played by pink marketing in its elements (product - price - promotion - distribution) in the stages of purchasing decision-making for Egyptian women, as well as identifying the impact of demographic factors (age - income - marital status - education level) on the relationship between pink marketing and decision-making. Egyptian women (before - during - after) to buy ready-made clothes.Important findings of the research: the necessity of conducting workshops and introductory seminars to understand the pros and cons of pink marketing for non-specialists, and focusing the efforts of marketers in the clothing sector on understanding the needs and desires of women and trying to segment the market sectors according to demographic criteria.The recommendations: the necessity of paying attention to the clothing sector, in particular, and the rest of the sectors in general, in pink marketing when planning marketing. Interest in taking feedback, opinions, suggestions and ideas from women who are constantly hesitant to market in commercial communities.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تأثير أبعاد التسويق الريادي فى تعزيز ثقة العميل من خلال المرونة التسـويقيـة: دراسة تطبيقية على عملاء البنوك التجارية بمحافظة الدقهلية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279753.html</link>
      <description>تتناول هذه الدراسة بيان دور المرونة التسـويقيـة وتأثيرها فى العلاقة بين التسويق الريـادى وتعزيز ثقة العميل بالتطبيق على عملاء البنوك التجارية بمحافظة الدقهلية. وكذلك بيان التأثير المباشر للتسويق الريـادى على المرونة التسـويقيـة والتحقق من دراسة الأثر المباشر للتسويق الريـادى على ثقة العميل، وكذلك معرفة دراسة الأثر المباشر للمرونة التسـويقيـة على ثقة العميل، وذلك بالتطبيق على عملاء البنوك التجارية العاملة بمحافظة الدقهلية.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; كما تهدف تلك الدراسة إلى معرفة الدور الوسيط للمرونة التسـويقيـة فى توضيح وبيان أثر العلاقة بين التسويق الريـادى وثقة العميل، استخدم الباحث المنهج الوصفى التحليلى والاستقصاء كأداة رئيسية لجمع البيانات، ويشمل مجتمع هذة الدراسة على عملاء البنوك التجارية العاملة بمحافظة الدقهلية والتي تمثل (40) بنك بإجمالى عدد (3920) فرع بالمحافظة. لذا قام الباحث بسحب عينة عشوائية منتظمة من المترددين على تلك البنوك، ويبلغ حجمها (384) مفردة. وقد توصلت الدراسة إلى إن التسويق الريادي يؤثر تأثيراً معنوياً وإيجابياً في جميع أبعاد المرونة التسـويقيـة، وقد جاء متغير مرونة التنفيذ في المرتبة الأولى تأثراً بالتسويق الريادي(96%)، أما مرونة المشاركة فقد جاءت في المرتبة الثانية تأثراً بالتسويق الريادي(93%)، وأخيراً جاءت مرونة التفاعل المرتبة الأخيرة تأثراً بالتسويق الريـادى(87%). كما تبين إن التسويق الريادي يؤثر تأثيراً مباشراً معنوياً وإيجابياً في ثقة العميل(95%). إن جميع أبعاد المرونة التسـويقيـة تؤثر تأثيراً معنوياً وإيجابياً في ثقة العميل(86%)، وقد جاء متغير مرونة المشاركة في المرتبة الأولى تأثيراً في ثقة العميل أما مرونة التفاعل فقد جاءت في المرتبة الثانية تأثيراً في ثقة العميل وأخيراً جاءت مرونة التنفيذ في المرتبة الأخيرة تأثيراً في ثقة العميل، وذلك بالتطبيق على عملاء البنوك التجارية العاملة بمحافظة الدقهلية.This study deals with the statement of the role of marketing flexibility and its impact on the relationship between entrepreneurial marketing and enhancing customer confidence by applying to commercial bank customers in Dakahlia Governorate. As well as showing the direct impact of entrepreneurial marketing on marketing flexibility and verifying the study of the direct impact of entrepreneurial marketing on customer confidence, as well as knowing the study of the direct impact of marketing flexibility on customer confidence, by applying it to clients of commercial banks operating in Dakahlia Governorate.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; This study also aims to know the mediating role of marketing flexibility in clarifying and explaining the impact of the relationship between entrepreneurial marketing and customer trust. (3920) branch in the governorate. Therefore, the researcher drew a regular random sample from those who frequent those banks, and its size is (384) individuals. The study found that entrepreneurial marketing has a moral and positive impact on all dimensions of marketing flexibility, and the flexibility of implementation variable came in the first place affected by entrepreneurial marketing (96%), while flexibility of participation came in second place affected by entrepreneurial marketing (93%), and finally the flexibility of interaction ranked last affected by entrepreneurial marketing (87%). It was also found that entrepreneurial marketing has a direct moral and positive impact on customer confidence (95%). All dimensions of marketing flexibility have a positive and moral impact on customer confidence (86%). Interaction came in the second place influencing the customer's confidence, and finally the flexibility of implementation came in the last place, influencing the trust of the customer, by applying to the clients of commercial banks operating in Dakahlia Governorate.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور الكفاءة الذاتية المالية لمتخذي قرارات الاستثمار في ضوء التمويل السلوكي</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279754.html</link>
      <description>الهدف: استهدف البحث دراسة تأثير التمويل السلوكي على قرارات الاستثمار عند توسيط الكفاءة الذاتية المالية بالتطبيق على المستثمرين بالبورصة المصرية.المنهجية: اعتمد الباحث على المنهج الوصفي التحليلي، ولتحقيق هدف البحث تم تصميم استبيان كأداة لجمع البيانات من عينة بلغ حجمها (692) مفردة وتم استقصاء آرائهم باستخدام الاستبيان عبر الإنترنت باستخدام نموذج (Forms Google) وتم التأكد من موثوقية وصلاحية الاستبيان. وقد تم اختبار فرضيات الدارسة من خلال تطبيق نموذج المعادلات الهيكلية (SEM) Structural Equation&amp;amp;nbsp;Modeling.النتائج: أسفرت النتائج عما يلي: (1) يوجد تأثير معنوي للعوامل السلوكية على صانعي قرار الاستثمار الفردي في البورصة المصرية. (2) يوجد تأثير معنوي للعوامل الديموغرافية على صانعي قرار الاستثمار الفردي في البورصة المصرية. (3) يوجد تأثير معنوي للتمويل السلوكي على الكفاءة الذاتية المالية للمستثمرين في البورصة المصرية. (4) يوجد تأثير معنوي للكفاءة الذاتية المالية على صانعي قرار الاستثمار الفردي في البورصة المصرية. (5) يوجد تأثير معنوي للتمويل السلوكي على صانعي قرار الاستثمار الفردي في البورصة المصرية عند توسيط الكفاءة الذاتية المالية، ويوصي الباحث بضرورة تجنب العوامل السلوكية الخاطئة في اتخاذ القرارات الاستثمارية، لأن تجنب مثل هذه العوامل يتيح للمستثمرين أن يصلوا إلى قرارات أكثر عقلانية في ظل وجود كفاءة ذاتية ماليةObjective: The research aimed to study the effect of behavioral finance on investment decisions when mediating financial self-efficacy by applying it to investors in the Egyptian Stock Exchange.Methodology: The researcher relied on the descriptive analytical approach, and to achieve the goal of the research, a questionnaire was designed as a tool to collect data from a sample composed of (692) individual, their opinions were surveyed using the electronic questionnaire, and it was designed on the basis of Google Forms engine models&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;to suit the nature of the study. The credibility and validity of the questionnaire were confirmed. The study's hypotheses were tested by applying structural equation modeling (SEM).Results: The results showed the following: (1) There is a significant effect of behavioral factors on individual investment decision makers in the Egyptian Stock Exchange. (2) There is a significant effect of demographic factors on individual investment decision makers in the Egyptian Stock Exchange. (3) There is no significant effect of behavioral finance on the financial self-efficacy of investors in the Egyptian Stock Exchange. (4) There is a significant effect of financial self-efficacy on individual investment decision makers in the Egyptian Stock Exchange. (5) There is a significant effect of behavioral finance on individual investment decision makers in the Egyptian Stock Exchange when mediating financial self-efficacy, and the researcher recommends to avoid wrong behavioral factors in making investment decisions, because avoiding such factors allows investors to reach more rational decisions in the presence of financial self-efficacy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر الثورة الصناعية الرابعة على تحسين منظومة التعليم الجامعي بمصر بالتطبيق على جامعة دمياط</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279755.html</link>
      <description>تناولت الدراسة أثر الثورة الصناعية الرابعة على تحسين منظومة التعليم الجامعي بمصر بالتطبيق على جامعة دمياط ، وتهدف الدراسة للربط بين من مفهوم الثورة الصناعية الرابعة وتأثيراتها المختلفة التي تمثل أبعادها وهي : تفعيل عناصر منظومة الثورة الصناعية الرابعة التي تؤثر على أعضاء هيئة التدريس وتفعيل عناصر منظومة الثورة الصناعية الرابعة التي تؤثر على الطالب، تفعيل عناصر منظومة الثورة الصناعية الرابعة التي تؤثرعلى بيئة التعليم الجامعي، والوصول إلى تحسين منظومة التعليم الجامعي بمصر من خلال عينة 60 مفردة من أعضاء هيئة التدريس بجامعة دمياط وتم التحليل للبيانات بواسطة برنامج SPSS ، وتم إثبات الفروض الإحصائية، وتوصلت الباحثة إلي وجود علاقة&amp;amp;nbsp; ذات دلالة إحصائية بين تفعيل عناصر منظومة الثورة الصناعية الرابعة وبين تحسين منظومة التعليم الجامعي بمصر .The research dealt with the impact of the Fourth Industrial Revolution on improving the university education system in Egypt by applying to Damietta University, and aims to link between the concept of the Fourth Industrial Revolution and its various effects that represent its dimensions: activating the elements of the Fourth Industrial Revolution system that affect faculty members, activating the elements of the Industrial Revolution system The fourth that affects the student, activating the elements of the Fourth Industrial Revolution system that affect the university education environment, and reaching the improvement of the university education system in Egypt, through a sample of 60 individual members of the faculty at Damietta University. The data was analyzed by the SPSS program, and the statistical hypotheses were proven, and he concluded that there is a statistically significant relationship between the activation of the elements of the Fourth Industrial Revolution system and the improvement of the university education system in Egypt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور التغير التنظيمي ومتطلبات التحول الرقمي لتحقيق ميزة تنافسية بالجامعات المصرية بالتطبيق علي كلية الزراعة جامعة الإسكندرية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279756.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;تهدف هذه الدراسة إلى التعرف على أثر إدارة التغير التنظيمي بأبعادها المتمثلة في&amp;amp;nbsp; (إمتلاك الرؤية، مهارات التغيير، نشر ثقافة التغيير، خطة التغيير، إدارة الموارد، إختيار الإستراتيجية الملائمة ) علي التحول الرقمي بمتطلباتة المختلفة ( المتطلبات الإدارية للمؤسسة، المتطلبات البشرية، المتطلبات التقنية، المتطلبات الأمنية، شبكات الإتصال ) بالمؤسسات الجامعية لتحقيق ميزة تنافسية بأبعادها في كلية الزراعة &amp;amp;ndash; جامعة الاسكندرية - وهذه الأبعاد تمثلت في ( موقع المؤسسة، معدل نمو الحصة السوقية، التكاليف بأنواعها، مرونة المؤسسة وسرعة التكييف، المعرفة )، وقد إعتمد الباحث في تناول الدراسة وعرضها على المنهج الوصفي لتناول الجانب المفاهيمي، والمنهج التحليلي في تناول الجانب التطبيقي للدراسة، وإستخدام إستمارة الإستقصاء كأداه لجمع البيانات الأولية، فقد تم توزيع عدد ( 120 ) إستمارة، وبعد جمعها وفحصها تبين أن عدد ( 84 ) إستمارة فقط صالحة للتحليل الإحصائي، وقد توصلت الدراسة إلى مجموعة من النتائج من أهمها وجود علاقة إرتباط قوية بين أثر التغير التنظيمي ومتطلبات تطبيق التحول الرقمي بالمؤسسات الجامعية لتحقيق ميزة تنافسية، بالإضافة إلى تقديم تصور مقترح لخطوات التحول الرقمي في المؤسسات التعليمية، كما أوصت الدراسة في نهايتها بضرورة الإسراع في المشروع القومي للتحول الرقمي الذي يعد من أهم أدوات تحقيق التنمية المستدامة والتي تنشدها القيادة السياسية، وتطوير بيئة العمل الجامعي وتقديم خدمات إلكترونية، والإنطلاق نحو الإقتصاد الرقمي.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; This study aims to identify the impact of managing organizational change in its dimensions (Ownership of vision, change skills, diffusion of change culture, change line, resource management, choice of appropriate strategy) On digital transformation with its various application requirements (human resources, transformative leadership, organizational culture, strategy) University institutions to achieve a competitive advantage in their dimensions at the Faculty of Agriculture - University of Alexandria, and these dimensions have been represented by A number were distributed. 120 After collection and examination, only 84 forms were found to be suitable for statistical analysis. The study came up with a set of findings, the most important of which is a strong correlation between the impact of organizational change and the demands of digital transformation in university institutions to achieve a competitive advantage. The study also recommended that the National Digital Transformation Project, one of the most important tools for achieving sustainable development, be accelerated by political leadership, develop the university work environment and provide electronic services, and move towards a digital economy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دراسة استطلاعية حول معوقات إدارة الجودة المؤثرة علي جودة أداء المورد البشري في منظمات التعليم الفني الصناعي في مصر</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279757.html</link>
      <description>يهدف هذا البحث الي تحليل المعوقات التي تواجه &amp;amp;nbsp;تطبيق ادارة الجودة في منظمات التعليم الفني الصناعي ،المحددة لجودة اداء العنصر البشري من المعلمين والاداريين القائمين بالتدريس بغرض التعرف علي ظواهر المشكلات والمعوقات التي تواجه قطاع التعليم الفني الصناعي في احد محافظات مصر وهي محافظة القاهره لما يمثله هذا القطاع من اهمية داخل هذه المحافظة بالنسبة لكافة محافظات مصر . وقد تم تقسيم المتغيرات المستقلة الي اربعة متغيرات تمثل&amp;amp;nbsp; المعوقات التي تواجه المنظومة التعليمية وهي متغيرات متعلقة بالتجهيزات والوحدات ،والعنصر البشري ،والطلاب ، والمناهج .كما قد تم تقسيم المتغيرات التابعة الي ثلاثة متغيرات تمثل جودة اداء العنصر البشري وهي مهارات التعليم ،والمهارات الادارية،ومهارات الاتصال . وقد تم تجميع 387 استمارة استقصاء من 500 استمارة استقصاء تم توزيعها بنسبة استجابة 77% . وذلك من خلال الاستعانة بالاساليب الاحصائية الوصفية وكذلك اختبارات الفروض من خلال استخدام برنامج SPSS.22 &amp;amp;nbsp;من اجل تحليل البيانات . وقد توصلت الدراسة الي ان هناك ارتفاع في قيمة المتوسط العام لكافة عناصر معوقات ادارة الجودة&amp;amp;nbsp; في المنظمات محل الدراسة ،حيث بلغ قيمة المتوسط العام لمعوقات ادارة الجودة 4.15 درجة&amp;amp;nbsp; ، وقد كانت المعوقات المتعلقة بالطلاب هي اعلي&amp;amp;nbsp; متوسط&amp;amp;nbsp; حيث بلغ قيمة متوسط المعوقات المتعلقة بالطلاب 4.45 يليها المعوقات المتعلقة بالتجهيزات والوحدات ثم المعوقات المتعلقة بالمناهج والتي تقارب قيمة المتوسط لكلاهما حيث بلغ 4.27 و 4.23 لكل منهما علي الترتيب ؛ بينما جاءت المعوقات المتعلقة بالعنصر البشري اقل قيمة متوسط من بين المعوقات كافة&amp;amp;nbsp; رغم ارتفاعها هي الاخري وفقا لمقياس ليكرت الخماسي ،حيث بلغ قيمة متوسط المعوقات المتعلقة بالعنصر البشري 3.64 درجة. وعلي الجانب الاخر فقد انخفضت قيمة المتوسط لكافة مؤشرات جودة اداء العنصر البشري ،حيث لم يتعدي قيمة المتوسط العام لجودة اداء العنصر البشري 2.48 درجة ، وقد كانت مهارات الاتصال اعلي قيمة متوسط&amp;amp;nbsp; لجودة اداء العنصر البشري حيث بلغت 3.29 درجة وهي تعتبر متوسطة وفقا لمقياس ليكرت الخماسي. واخيرا اقترحت الدراسة بعض التوصيات الخاصة لحل المشاكل المتعلقة بنظام التعليم الفني الصناعي في مصر من واقع نتائج الدراسة الحالية الي جانب تقديم بعض المقترحات للدراسات المستقبلية.This research aims to analyze the obstacles facing quality management in industrial technical education organizations, which determine the quality of the performance of the human element of teachers and administrators in charge of teaching, in order to identify the phenomena of problems and obstacles facing the technical industrial education sector in Egypt, The independent variables have been divided into four variables that represent the obstacles facing the educational system, which are variables related to equipment, units, the human element, students, and curricula. The dependent variables have also been divided into three variables that represent the quality of human performance, which are educational skills, administrative skills, and communication skills. A total of 387 questionnaires were collected from 500 questionnaires that were distributed with a response rate of 77%. This is done through the use of descriptive statistical methods as well as hypothesis tests through the use of the SPSS.22 program for data analysis. The study concluded that there is an increase in the general average value of all elements of quality management obstacles in the organizations under study, On the other hand, the average value of all indicators of the quality of human performance has decreased.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تأثير الخصائص الشخصية للرئيس التنفيذى على النمو المستدام للشركات المقيدة فى البورصة المصرية من خلال إدارة رأس المال العامل</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279758.html</link>
      <description>يهدف هذا البحث الى دراسة تأثير الخصائص الشخصية للرئيس التنفيذى على النمو المستدام للشركات المقيدة فى البورصة المصرية والتأثير المتوسط&amp;amp;nbsp; لإدارة رأس المال العامل على العلاقة بين الخصائص الشخصية للرئيس التنفيذى والنمو المستدام للشركاتوذلك في الفترة من 2012 إلى 2020. وفى سبيل تحقيق ذلك تم تطوير مجموعة من الفروض اعتمد الباحث فى اختبارها على استخدام اسلوب الانحدار المرجح. وقد اسفرت نتائج التحليل الاحصائى للبيانات على ان هناك مجموعة من المتغيرات والعوامل الاساسية التي تحدد معدل النمو المستدام للشركات فى الواقع المصرى وتلك المتغيرات هى الرافعة المالية؛ الربحية؛ معدل استخدام الأصول ومستوى التعليم المالى للرئيس التنفيذى. كذلك يتمتع الرؤساء التنفيذيين فى الشركات المصرية بالثقة الإدارية المرتفعة وذلك نظرا لاعتمادهم على استخدام الديون بنسبة اكبر من اعتمادهم على التمويل الداخلى لتمويل صافى رأس المال العامل. وأخيرا رأس المال العامل ليس له دور وسيط فى التأثير على العلاقة بين الخصائص الشخصية للرئيس التنفيذى ومعدل النمو المستدام للشركات فى الواقع المصرى.This research aims to study the effect of the CEO&amp;amp;rsquo;s personal characteristics on the sustainable growth of companies listed in the Egyptian Stock Exchange and the moderating effect of working capital management on the relationship between the CEO&amp;amp;rsquo;s personal characteristics and the sustainable growth of companies, during the period from 2012 to 2020. In order to achieve this, some hypotheses were developed The researcher relied in her testing on the use of the weighted least square method. The results of the statistical analysis of the data show that there are a set of basic variables and factors that determine the sustainable growth rate of companies in the Egyptian reality, and these variables are the financial leverage; profitability; Asset utilization rate and CEO financial education level. Also, CEOs in Egyptian companies enjoy administrative overconfidence, due to their reliance on the use of debt at a greater rate than their reliance on internal financing to finance the net working capital. Finally, working capital has no moderating role in influencing the relationship between the personal characteristics of the CEO and the rate of sustainable growth of companies in the Egyptian reality.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور القيادة الأخلاقية في الحد من الأزمات "بالتطبيق على ديوان عام محافظة القاهرة "</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279760.html</link>
      <description>استهدفت الدراسة توضح دور ممارسات القيادة الأخلاقية وعلاقتها بتحقيق الحد من الأزمات. &amp;amp;nbsp;تعد القيادة الأخلاقية المنبثقة من منظومة إدارية سليمة هي المحرك الفعال لنهضة الأمم والشعوب وتقدمها، والإدارة الأكثر فاعلية للتغيير وصناعة المستقبل، لما لها من آثار إيجابية في دفع حركة المجتمع وبنائه والارتقاء به والحد من الأزمات، في ظل الأزمات العالمية. وذلك من خلال إعداد القيادات الناجحة والقادرة على التغيير والابتكار، لحل المشكلات واتخاذ القرارات في المواقف المناسبة بناء على قاعدة تعزيز السلوك الأخلاقي في منظومة العمل والعلاقات ومواجهة الأزمات.توصلت الدراسة إلى وجود علاقة ارتباط معنوية إيجابية ذات دلالة إحصائية بين القيادة الأخلاقية وبين الحد من الازمات. مما يدعم التوصية بضرورة الإسراع والعناية والاهتمام بالقيادة الاخلاقية في المنظمات، فالقيادة الأخلاقية تعد بوابة نجاح إستراتيجية مركزية لأي مؤسسة تنشد النمو وتحقيق الغايات، فهي تحقق العدالة والشفافية، وتشجع العمل الجماعي المشترك، والمشاركة في صنع القرار، والاهتمام بالمرؤوسين وتعزيز نموهم، والتخلي عن المفهوم التقليدي للقيادة، وذلك وفق إطار أخلاقي إنساني يتزامن فيه الارتقاء بأداء المؤسسة ونوعية إنتاجها مع الاعتناء بالأفراد وتطويرهم وتحفيزهم وتعزيز دورهم.The study aimed to clarify the role of ethical leadership practices and their relationship to achieving crisis reduction. Ethical leadership emanating from a sound educational system is the effective engine for the renaissance and progress of nations and peoples, and the most effective management of change and industry of the future, because of its positive effects in advancing the movement of society, building and upgrading it and reducing crises, in light of global crises. And that is through preparing successful leaders who are capable of change and innovation, to solve problems and make decisions in appropriate situations based on the basis of promoting ethical behavior in the work system, relationships and confronting crises.The study found a positive and statistically significant correlation between ethical leadership and crisis reduction. Which supports the recommendation of the need to expedite, take care, and pay attention to ethical leadership in organizations. Ethical leadership is a central strategic gateway to any organization that seeks growth and achieve goals. It achieves justice and transparency, encourages joint teamwork, participates in decision-making, cares for subordinates and promotes their growth, and abandons the traditional concept. For leadership, in accordance with a humane ethical framework in which the improvement of the performance of the institution and the quality of its production coincides with the care, development, motivation and enhancement of individuals and their role.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>علاقة ابعاد راس المال النفسي الايجابي بدعم الثقة التنظيمية وجودة الحياة الوظيفية لدي عينة من الموظفين الاداريين ببعض شركات قطاع البترول</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279761.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث الحالي الي اكتشاف العلاقة بين ابعاد راس المال النفسي و دعم الثقة التنظيمية و جودة الحياة الوظيفية وكذلك الكشف عن طبيعة ومدي العلاقة بين متغيرات النوع وعدد سنوات الخبرة وعدد الدورات التدريبية لدي عينة من الموظفين الاداريين ببعض شركات قطاع البترول، وقد إعتمدت الباحثة علي عينة من الموظفين الإدارين ببعض شركات قطاع البترول قوامها 120 موظف اداري ( من اربعة شركات) وتم اجراء التحليل الاحصائي واختبار الفروض ، وخلص البحث الحالي الي وجود علاقه ارتباطية موجبة بين متغيرات البحث راس المال النفسي وجودة الحياة الوظيفية ودعم الثقة التنظيمية ، وكذلك وجود فروق داله احصائيا بين افراد العينة من مرتفعي راس المال النفسي ومنخفضي راس المال النفسي مما يؤكد طردية العلاقة الايجابية بين راس المال النفسي وجودة الحياة الوظيفية ودعم الثقة التنظيمية ، كما كشف البحث الحالي عن طبيعة ومدي العلاقة بين متغيرات النوع وعدد سنوات الخبرة وعدد الدورات التدريبية بمتغيرات البحث .The current research aims to discover the relationship between the dimensions of psychological capital, support for organizational confidence, and quality of work life, as well as revealing the nature and extent of the relationship between gender variables, number of years of experience, and number of training courses for a sample of administrative employees in some petroleum sector companies. The administrative staff of some petroleum sector companies, consisting of 120 administrative employees (from four companies), was carried out statistical analysis and hypothesis testing. The sample is high in psychological capital and low in psychological capital, which confirms the positive relationship between psychological capital, quality of work life and support for organizational confidence, and the current research revealed the nature and extent of the relationship between gender variables, number of years of experience, and number of training courses with research variables.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>القيادة التكيفية وتأثيرها على الدمج التنظيمي والسلوك الابتكاري للعاملين أثناء جائحة كورونا دراسة تطبيقية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279762.html</link>
      <description>اهتمت هذه الدراسة بشكل أساسي بدور القيادة التكيفية في تحقيق الدمج التنظيمي وأثرهما على السلوك الابتكاري للعاملين بالمستشفيات والمراكز الطبية المتخصصة بجامعة المنصورة ولتحقيق ذلك تناولت الدراسة أبعاد القيادة التكيفية (التأثير والتحفيز، الاهتمام برؤية المنظمة، الإدارة، تنمية رأس المال البشري، التعلم، السلوك الأخلاقي، التعاون، المبادرة، التواصل، صناعة القرار، والتغيير) وأبعاد الدمج التنظيمي العام (الدمج التنظيمي، الدمج المحايد، الدمج المتناقض، وعدم الدمج التنظيمي). أيضاً دراسة تأثير أبعاد القيادة التكيفية على الدمج التنظيمي والسلوك الابتكاري ،ودراسة تأثير الدمج التنظيمي على السلوك الابتكاري وأخيراً التعرف على الدور الوسيط للدمج التنظيمي في العلاقة بين أبعاد القيادة التكيفية و السلوك الابتكاري ،وأجريت الدراسة على عينة قوامها 384 مفردة من العاملين في هذه المؤسسات متضمناً العاملين في مجال الرعاية الصحية من الأطباء وهيئة التمريض والإداريون، وتوصلت الدراسة إلى نتائج أهمها أولاً عدم اتفاق مفردات العينة على أبعاد القيادة التكيفية بالإضافة إلى عدم اتفاقهم على مدي ممارسة أبعاد الدمج التنظيمي وانتشار ممارسة الأشكال المختلفة للدمج التنظيمي بدرجات متباينة، &amp;amp;nbsp;ثانياً وجود تأثير معنوي لأبعاد القيادة التكيفية في الدمج التنظيمي وتفسر هذه الأبعاد (38.5%) من التباين في الدمج التنظيمي ،ثالثاً ووجود تأثير معنوي للدمج التنظيمي في السلوك الابتكاري للعاملين ،وأخيراً يتوسط الدمج التنظيمي كلياً العلاقة بين أبعاد القيادة التكيفية المتمثلة في التأثير والتحفيز، والإدارة وبين السلوك الابتكاري للعاملين في المؤسسات موضع التطبيق ،كما يتوسط هذه العلاقة جزئياً المتعلقة بالاهتمام برؤية المنظمة ،تنمية رأس المال البشري ،السلوك الأخلاقي ،التعاون ،المبادرة ،صناعة القرار ،في حين لا يتوسط تلك العلاقة فيما يتعلق بالتعلم، التواصل، التغيير.This study tried basically the role of the adaptive leadership in achieving organizational identification and their effect on innovative work behavior in Hospitals and specialized medical centers in Mansoura University, To achieve this, the researcher aimed to search the dimensions of general organizational identification (organizational identification, disidentification, neutral identification ,ambivalent identification) and adaptive leadership (influencing and motivating, learning, managing, envisioning, teaming, initiating, ethical behavior, developing human capital, communicating, decision-making, changing,) and also aimed to determine the impact the dimensions of adaptive leadership on&amp;amp;nbsp; organizational identification and innovative work behavior, In addition to addressing the impact of the organizational identification on innovative work behavior as well as to study the intermediary role played by the organizational identification in the effect of the dimensions of adaptive leadership impact on innovative work behavior, and the study was conducted on a sample of 384 single of workers, and the study found the results of the most important first disagreement sample on the dimensions of adaptive leadership, in addition to disagreeing on the dimensions of organizational identification, secondly the presence of significant effect of the dimensions of adaptive leadership impact on organizational identification and these dimensions account for %38.5 of the variation in organizational Identification, thirdly the presence of significant effect of organizational identification on innovative work behavior, and finally having a role of total mediator for the direction of the organizational identification to the impact the dimensions of adaptive leadership (&amp;amp;nbsp; influencing and motivating, managing ) impact on innovative work behavior to the workers in these institutions , this relationship is partly mediated by(Envisioning, teaming, initiating, ethical behavior, developing human capital, , decision-making) &amp;amp;nbsp;while that relationship is not mediated with respect to (learning ,communicating, changing)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تأثير الاستراتيجية البيئية التفاعلية مقابل الاستراتيجية البيئية الاستباقية على التنمية المستدامة للصناعات الغذائية: دور إدارة الموارد البشرية الخضراء متغيرا وسيطا</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279763.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث إلى تحليل تأثير توسيط إدارة الموارد البشرية الخضراء في العلاقة بين تأثير الاستراتيجية البيئية التفاعلية مقابل الاستراتيجية البيئية الاستباقية على التنمية المستدامة للصناعات الغذائية ، وذلك بالتطبيق على 300 مفردة من المديرين التنفيذيين ومديري الموارد البشرية بالصناعات الغذائية المسجلة في الهيئة القومية لسلامة الغذاء &amp;amp;nbsp;بالقائمة البيضاء بأسلوب الحصر الشامل ، &amp;amp;nbsp;وقد اعتمد البحث على التحليل العاملي التوكيدي لاختبار ثبات وصدق مقاييس متغيرات البحث ، وكذلك على نمذجة المعادلة الهيكلية باستخدام تحليل المسار لاختبار فروض البحث .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وقد توصل البحث إلى مجموعة من النتائج أهمها: تؤثر الاستراتيجية البيئية التفاعلية تأثيرا سلبيا مباشرا مقابل التأثير الإيجابي المباشر للاستراتيجية البيئية الاستباقية على أبعاد التنمية المستدامة للمنظمات التي تتضمن الأداء البيئي والأداء الاجتماعي والأداء الاقتصادي. تؤثر الاستراتيجية البيئية التفاعلية تأثيرا سلبيا مباشرا مقابل التأثير الإيجابي المباشر للاستراتيجية البيئية الاستباقية على إدارة الموارد البشرية الخضراء. وتؤثر إدارة الموارد البشرية الخضراء تأثيرا إيجابيا مباشرا دالا على الأداء البيئي، والأداء الاجتماعي والأداء الاقتصادي، وأن التأثير الإيجابي لإدارة الموارد البشرية الخضراء أكبر تأثيرا في حالة الإستراتيجية البيئية الاستباقية مقارنة بالاستراتيجية البيئية التفاعلية. وإن إدارة الموارد البشرية الخضراء تتوسط العلاقة بين كل من الاستراتيجيتين البيئتين وأبعاد التنمية المستدامة للأداء البيئي والأداء الاجتماعي والأداء الاقتصادي. وقد ناقش البحث النتائج واقترح بعض التوصيات.The research aims to analyze the effect of mediating green human resources management in the relationship between the impact of the reactive environmental strategy versus the proactive environmental strategy on the sustainable development of the food industries, by applying to 300 executive directors and human resource managers in the food industries registered in the National Food Safety Authority in the whitelist in a comprehensive inventory method. The research relied on confirmatory factor analysis to test the reliability and validity of the measures of the research variables, as well as on structural equation modeling using path analysis to test the research hypothesesThe research concludes with a set of results, the most important of which are: The reactive environmental strategy has a direct negative impact versus the direct positive impact of the proactive environmental strategy on the dimensions of sustainable development for organizations that include environmental performance, social performance, and economic performance. A reactive environmental strategy has a direct negative effect versus a direct positive impact of a proactive environmental strategy on green human resource management. Green human resource management has a direct positive impact on environmental performance, social performance, and economic performance, and the positive impact of green human resource management is greater in the case of a proactive environmental strategy compared to a reactive environmental strategy. The management of green human resources mediates the relationship between each of the two environmental strategies and the dimensions of sustainable development: environmental performance, social performance, and economic performance. The research discussed the results and suggested some recommendations.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>الدور الوسيط للتصنيع الأخضر في العلاقة بين المسئولية البيئية للمنشآت و استدامة الأداء في ضوء رؤية مصر 2030 ، دراسة تطبيقية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279768.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;ظهرت في الأونة الأخيرة العديد من القضايا الاستراتيجية التي تواجه العالم بأجمعه ، و لعل من أهمها قضية ( تغير المناخ ، إهدار الموارد الطبيعية ) الناتجة عن ارتفاع معدلات&amp;amp;nbsp; الضرر والتلوث البيئي،و لذلك&amp;amp;nbsp; يتوجه العالم &amp;amp;nbsp;بأجمعه للبحث عن حلول جذرية لمواجهة تلك القضايا وهو ما تسعى له رؤية مصر 2030 لتحقيق التنمية المستدامة بمحاورها الثلاث، ولذلك فهدف الدراسة هو معرفة الدورالوسيط للتصنيع الأخضر في العلاقة بين المسئولية البيئية للمنشآت و استدامة الأداء، بالتطبيق على قطاع التشييد و البناء بمصر، و لقد تم الاعتماد على استخدام الاساليب الإحصائية التي تلائم طبيعة الدراسة لاختبار الفروض مثل اختبار نمذجة الهياكل ،حيث وجد أن هناك تأثير إيجابي بين المتغيرات الخاصة بمحاور النموذج الخاص بالدراسة ك (المسئولية البيئية ، التصنيع الأخضر ،الأداء (الاقتصادي ، الاجتماعي ، البيئي) المستدام ، كما يلعب المتغير الخاص ب( التصنيع الأخضر) دور الوسيط في العلاقة بين المتغييرين،&amp;amp;nbsp; كما تبينت من نتائج الدراسة الأهمية المتقاربة لجميع تلك المتغيرات.Many strategic issues have been emerged at the last few years like (The climate changes, The waste of natural resources) that was caused by high level of pollution and environmental damages, which made the whole world searching for radical solutions to these life-threatening problems. So, the main goal of this study is to identify the mediating role of the green manufacturing in the relation between environmental responsibility and Sustainability of performance according to Egypt&amp;amp;rsquo;s vision 2030, and to test the hypothesis, some statistical methods were used like (SME).The study concluded that there is a positive effect of both the variables of (environmental responsibility, green manufacturing practices) on the sustainable performance, the green manufacturing variable plays the role of mediator of the relationship between other variables, and there is a convergence in the level of importance between the variables.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining The Effect of Organizational DNA on Strategic Inertia: An Evidence from The Egyptian Textiles and Garments Companies</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279770.html</link>
      <description>This paper investigates the antecedents of strategic inertia in the Egyptian textile and garments industry. Despite the importance of flexibility in this dynamic industry, empirical evidence points out the high levels of inertia. Based on organizational ecology and institutional inertia theories, this paper argues that the nature of decision rights, information, motivators, and organizational structure significantly affects strategic inertia. The study also compares Egyptian public and private textile and garments manufacturers&amp;amp;rsquo; DNA influence on strategic inertia. Self-administered surveys and various statistical tools were used to test the research hypotheses empirically. The results show a significant negative effect of the organizational DNA genes and cognitive, socio-cognitive, and behavioral inertia, except for the significant positive effect of information on cognitive inertia. It is suggested that future research investigates several factors that may mediate or moderate this relationship. Finally, practical implications for senior managers and the human resource management staff are discussed at the end of the paper.&amp;amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mediating Role of Organizational Citizenship Behavior on the Relationship Between Entrepreneurial Leadership and Employees' Creativity: New Evidence from PLS-SEM Method</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279771.html</link>
      <description>أجبرت المنافسة الشديدة الصناعات والشركات على أن تمييز نفسها عن منافسيها من خلال الاستثمار في موظفيها ، الذين يُنظر إليهم على أنهم أحد الأصول الأكثر قيمة في أي شركة. الغرض من هذا البحث هو التحقق في العلاقة بين القيادة الريادية وإبداع الموظفين ودراسة الدور الوسيط لسلوك المواطنة التنظيمية في هذه العلاقة. باستخدام تصميم البحث الكمي ، تم جمع البيانات من 400 موظف في البنوك الأجنبية في مصر. تم تحليل نتائج البحث باستخدام تقنية نمذجة المعادلة الهيكلية. أشارت النتائج إلى أن القيادة الريادية لها تأثير كبير على إبداع الموظفين ، علاوة على ذلك ، يتوسط سلوك المواطنة التنظيمية هذه العلاقة. يكشف هذا البحث عن الدور المهم للقيادة الريادية في تعزيز إبداع الموظفين في البنوك الأجنبية في مصر. يساهم هذا البحث بطريقة جديدة في نظرية القيادة الريادية من خلال تقديم صورة أكثر تفصيلاً للعمليات المختلفة لتأثير القيادة الريادية على إبداع الموظفين. تهدف هذه الدراسة إلى فحص دور قادة ريادة الأعمال في تعزيز إبداع الموظف من خلال زيادة سلوك المواطنه التنظيميه للموظفين.و تشير نتائج هذه الدراسة إلى أن القائد الريادى&amp;amp;nbsp; يمكن أن يساعد في تحفيز إبداع الموظف من خلال سلوك المواطنة التنظيمية. علاوة على ذلك ، فإنه يوفر فهماً أعمق لمفهوم القيادة الريادية وآثاره الإدارية والنظرية.Today, intense competition across industries has compelled businesses to differentiate themselves from their rivals by investing in their staff, who are regarded as one of the most valuable assets of any corporation. The purpose of this research is to investigate the relationship between Entrepreneurial Leadership (EL) and Employees&amp;amp;rsquo; Creativity (EC) and examine the mediating role of Organizational Citizenship Behavior (OCB) in this relationship. Using quantitative research design, data were collected from 400 employees of foreign banks in Egypt. The results of the research were analyzed using a structural equation modeling technique. The findings indicated that entrepreneurial leadership has a significant impact on employees' creativity, Moreover, Organizational Citizenship Behavior mediates this relationship. This research uncovers the important role of entrepreneurial leadership in driving employee Creativity in foreign banks in Egypt. This research contributes to entrepreneurial leadership theory in a novel way by offering a more detailed picture of the varying processes that transmit the impact of entrepreneurial leadership on employees' creativity. This study is to examine the role of entrepreneurial leaders in fostering employee creativity through OCB.The findings of this study suggest that entrepreneurial leaders can help stimulate employee creativity through their organizational citizenship behavior. Furthermore, it provides a deeper understanding of the concept of entrepreneurial leadership and its managerial and theoretical implications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mediating Role of Supply Chain Management between Social Media Networks and Service Quality</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279775.html</link>
      <description>Within the context of social media networks and quality service, this study analysised the functions that social media can play as a mediator. The business-to-business (B2B) interaction that exists between the fast-food industry in Egypt is the primary subject of this study to analyze the mediating role of supply chain management. The study covers the area of Cairo, and data collection took place during the first quarter of the year 2022. The sample size was 462, and the response rate was 84.77%. It was discovered that social media networks have an effect on the flow of information throughout the supply chain as well as the quality of services provided in fast food apps. Significant changes have been brought about in both the supply chain and the quality of services as a result of the influence of social media. It helped explain why the supply chain's performance changed, which led to a better quality of service.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eco-friendly initiatives and corporate reputation: the mediating effect of corporate social responsibility</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279776.html</link>
      <description>In contemporary global competition, businesses have been under growing pressure from various stakeholders to manage rare resources and investigate the environmental impact of their actions. The need for sustainable development and green marketing has gained significant traction because of heightened public awareness of several environmental issues. The goal of sustainability is depicted as a long-term process that requires reconciling environmental concerns with social and economic ones. Green marketing is becoming increasingly popular as a means for companies to demonstrate their commitment to corporate social responsibility while gaining a competitive advantage in the marketplace and improving their corporate reputation. This research investigates the effect of green eco-friendly initiatives on corporate reputation. In addition, it examines the effect of corporate social responsibility as a mediator between the green activities implemented by the hotels and their corporate reputation. The researcher selected the Green Star hotels in the Red Sea in Egypt. Data was gathered through online self-administered questionnaires from a sample of 384 hotel guests. Statistical analysis was undertaken to examine the collected data using the proper statistical techniques and tests. Results revealed that green/eco-friendly activities significantly positively affect a hotel's corporate reputation. Furthermore, corporate social responsibility mediates the relationship between green/eco-friendly activities and corporate reputation. The results revealed that green/eco-friendly activities have a significant positive indirect effect on corporate reputation in the presence of corporate social responsibility. Besides, the results also demonstrate that eco-friendly and CSR activities may benefit developing and emerging economies. Research findings were discussed to reflect the researcher's interpretation and perception of the outcomes. The research provides hotel marketers with practical implications for using eco-friendly and CSR initiatives.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تـوسـيط الوعي بالعلامة التجارية في العـلاقـة بين التسويق عبر المؤثرين على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي وسلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات ( دراسة تطبيقية على مستخدمي منصات التواصل الاجتماعي )</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_287547.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; تهدف هذه الدراسة إلى قياس تأثير أبعاد التسويق عبر المؤثرين على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي (جاذبية المؤثرين، و خبرة المؤثرين، و جدارة المؤثرين بالثقة) على سلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات عند توسيط الوعي بالعلامة التجارية. وقد تم الاعتماد علي قائمة استقصاء إلكترونية قوامها 367مفردة في جمع البيانات الأولية اللازمة لاختبار فروض الدراسة علي مستخدمي منصات التواصل الاجتماعي &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;( مثل : فيسبوك&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Facebook ، ويوتيوب YouTube، و إنستجرام Instagram) من السيدات اللاتي يتعاملن مع منصات التواصل الاجتماعي واللاتي ويتابعن أحد الشخصيات المؤثرة على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي خلال فترة الدراسة .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وتوصلت الدراسة إلى وجود تأثير معنوي إيجابي لأبعاد التسويق عبر المؤثرين على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي (جاذبية المؤثرين ، و جدارة المؤثرين بالثقة) على سلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات وعدم وجود تأثير معنوي إيجابي لخبرة المؤثرين على سلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات، &amp;amp;nbsp;كما توصلت إلى وجود تأثير معنوي لأبعاد التسويق عبر المؤثرين على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي (جاذبية المؤثرين ، و خبرة المؤثرين، و جدارة المؤثرين بالثقة) على الوعي بالعلامة التجارية ، وتوصلت أيضًا إلى وجود تأثير معنوي إيجابي للوعي بالعلامة التجارية على سلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات،وأظهرت النتائج انه يختلف التأثير المعنوي لأبعاد التسويق عبر المؤثرين على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي (جاذبية المؤثرين ، و خبرة المؤثرين، و جدارة المؤثرين بالثقة) على سلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات عند توسيط الوعي بالعلامة التجارية ، كما أشارت النتائج إلى وجود تأثير معنوي للخصائص الديموجرافية (السن ، ومستوى التعليم ، ومستوي الدخل الشهري) على العلاقة بين أبعاد التسويق عبر المؤثرين على منصات التواصل الاجتماعي و سلوك الشراء الاندفاعي للملابس لدى السيدات.The aim of this study is to measure the impact of influencer marketing on social media platforms dimensions (influencer attractiveness, influencer experience, and influencer trustworthiness) on Impulsive buying behavior of women's clothes when brand awareness is mediator. It has been relying on An electronic survey list Single 367 strong in the preliminary data collection necessary for testing hypotheses for research on users of social media platforms (such as: Facebook, YouTube, and Instagram) from women who interact with social media platforms and who follow an influential figure on social media platforms during the study period.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study found a positive moral effect of the social media influencers marketing dimensions (influencers Attractive,and Influencers trustworthy) on the Impulsive buying behavior of women's clothes and no found a positive moral effect of the Influencers Experience on Impulsive buying behavior of women's clothes, It&amp;amp;nbsp; also found a positive moral impact of social media influencers marketing dimensions (influencers Attractive, Influencers Experience ,and Influencers trustworthy) on brand awareness, a positive moral effect of brand awareness on Impulsive buying behavior of women's clothes, and the results showed that the moral effect of the influencers marketing dimensions (influencers Attractive,and Influencers trustworthy) on Impulsive buying behavior of women's clothes when the brand awareness is mediator, and there is the&amp;amp;nbsp; moral effect of&amp;amp;nbsp; the demographic characteristics of (age, education level, monthly income level) on the relationship between the dimensions of social media influencers marketing and Impulsive buying behavior of women's clothes.&amp;amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>قياس كفاءة موانئ الحاويات الليبية والموانئ المجاورة لها بالبحر المتوسط</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279779.html</link>
      <description>خلال العقود السابقة؛ حدثت زيادة هائلة في حجم البضاعة المنقوله بحرًا. وتعد صناعة النقل البحري وسيلة النقل المهيمنة في التجارة الدولية؛ لأنها الوسيلة الأكثر فعالية من حيث تكلفة نقل البضائع. تعد الموانئ البحرية العمود الفقري للتجارة الدولية، وتعتبر موانئ ومحطات الحاويات مكونات أساسية للإقتصاد الحديث ويرجع ذلك إلى مزاياها، بما في ذلك كفاءة التكلفة والوقت. تهدف الدراسة لقياس كفاءة محطات الحاويات الليبية والموانئ المجاورة لها بإستخدام نموذج Data Envelopment Analysis خلال الأعوام من 2010 حتي العام 2020؛ بهدف معرفة مستوي كفائتها ومواطن ضعفها لعمل التوصيات اللازمة لرفع كفاءة المحطات الليبية بين الموانئ المجاورة لها في البحر المتوسط.During the previous decads; there has been an increase in the volume of goods transported by sea. Maritime transport is the dominant mode of transport in international trade; it become the most effective modes of transfer goods. Seaports are the backbone of international, and basic ports and terminals are essential components of the economy and owe to their advantages, including cost and time efficient. This research aims to measure the efficiency of Libyan container terminals using Data Envelopment Analysis for the period between 2010 and 2020, to identify weaknesses area to make recommendations to enhance the efficiency of these ports between its neighboring ports in the Mediterranean.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The repercussions of Covid-19 and the Russian-Ukrainian war on shipping industry in Egypt</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279783.html</link>
      <description>شهد سوق الشحن إرتباكًا كبيرًا بسبب الهجمات الروسية على أوكرانيا، حيث تم تعليق عدد من حجوزات الخطوط الأوكرانية حتى مارس من العام المقبل 2023، مثل خط ملاحي ميرسك والذي يعتبر ثاني أهم خط ملاحي في العالم وتسببت الحرب الروسية الأوكرانية في تعطيل شحن البضائع بشدة حيث قامت القوات الروسية بقطع طرق الشحن، وقامت شركات الخدمات اللوجستية بتعليق خدماتها وارتفعت أسعار الشحن بشكل كبير. يهدف البحث إلى تحديد أثير الهجمات الروسية على الأوكرانيين وعلى النقل البحري والصناعة البحرية ككل وعلى النقل البحري في مصر خلال عام 2022. تعد هذه الدراسة مراجعة للأدبيات تاسابقة حيث تم إتباع النهج الاستقرائي.&#13;
Shipping market has witnessed a great confusion due to the Russian attacks on Ukrainian, as the number of lines suspended reservations from the Ukrainian until March next year 2023, such as the shipping line Maersk, which considered the second most important shipping line in the world. The Russia-Ukraine war is severely disrupting shipping freight. Russian forces are cutting off shipping routes, logistics firms are suspending services and freight rates are skyrocketing. This research aims to define the impact of the Russian attacks on Ukrainian on maritime transportation and maritime industry as a whole and maritime transportation in Egypt during the year 2022. This paper is a literature review paper; follows inductive research approach.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور الشهادات الاحترافية في تحقيق كفاءة الأداء دراسة تطبيقية على المنظمات الصحية بالمملكة العربية السعودية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279786.html</link>
      <description>هدفت الدراسة الى قياس دور الشهادات الاحترافية على كفاءة الأداء لدى منسوبي المنضمات الصحية بالمملكة العربية السعودية (تحقيق الأهداف، أداء العاملين، جودة الخدمة)، اعتمد الباحثون المنهج الوصفي والمنهج التحليلي. استخدمت الدراسة الاستبانة للدراسة الميدانية حيث تم تطبيقها على (299) من العاملين في المديرية العامة للشؤون الصحية بالمنطقة الشرقية، وقد توصلت الدراسة إلى نتائج أهمها:- وجود درجة تقدير مرتفعة للشهادات الاحترافية في المديرية العامة للشؤون الصحية بالمنطقة الشرقية، كما وبينت الدراسة وجود مستوى مرتفع من كفاءة الأداء، كما توصلت النتائج إلى أن متغير أداء العاملين كان في المرتبة الأولى من مغيرات كفاءة الأداء وبدرجة تقدير مرتفعة، تلاه متغير تحقيق الأهداف في المرتبة الثانية وبدرجة تقدير مرتفعة، وفي المرتبة الثالثة والأخيرة جاء متغير جودة الخدمة وبدرجة تقدير مرتفعة، وقد وبينت الدراسة أن هناك أثر ذو دلالة إحصائية للشهادات الاحترافية على كافة أبعاد كفاءة الأداء (تحقيق الأهداف، أداء العاملين، جودة الخدمة) في المديرية العامة للشؤون الصحية بالمنطقة الشرقية، وقد توصلت الدراسة إلى توصيات أهمها الاهتمام بالشهادات الاحترافية لما لها من أثر في كفاءة الأداء في المديرية العامة للشؤون الصحية بالمنطقة الشرقية.The study aimed to measure the role of professional certificates on employees of the General Directorate of Health Affairs in Saudi Arabia and its relationship to performance efficiency. The researchers adopted the descriptive method and the analytical method. The study used a questionnaire for the field study, which was applied to (299) employees in the General Directorate of Health Affairs in the Eastern Province. The findings confirmed the presence of a high degree of appreciation for professional certificates in the General Directorate, and showed a high level of performance efficiency. The results also found that the variable of employee performance was in the first rank among the variables of performance efficiency with a high degree of appreciation, followed by the variable of achieving goals, the variable of service quality with a high degree of appreciation. The study also showed that there is a statistically significant impact of professional certificates on all dimensions of performance efficiency (achievement of goals, employee performance, service quality). The study reached recommendations, the most important of which is the interest in professional certificates, as they have an impact on the efficiency of performance in the General Directorate of Health Affairs in the Eastern Province.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>THE EFFECT OF THE COVID-19 PANDEMIC ON FOOD SUPPLY CHAIN DISRUPTION IN DEVELOPED COUNTRIES</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279787.html</link>
      <description>Significance: This study represents a pioneering effort to unveil the consequences and effects of COVID-19 on the food industry in developed countries.Research Aim: This study describes the influences of the novel Coronavirus on the supply chain process of the food industry in developed countries.Research Methodology: An analysis was conducted on 15 industry articles and categorized into two major themes: the effect of each stage, and the general effects on all stages, each is further subdivided into additional themes. The systematic review is further supported by international case studies.Research Findings: Results show that firms are moving to localization, focusing on tier-1 supplier risk, e-commerce and changing their inventory policies, and evaluating alternative sources of supply to manage disruptions caused to their business operations amid the COVID-19 outbreak.Research Recommendations: It&amp;amp;rsquo;s recommended to pay more attention to protect the food supply against disruptions and to strengthen the design of the food supply chain in the future. Also, resilience in the food supply chain should be improved in the future. Supply chain firms can use the countermeasures provided in this study to mitigate the impact of COVID-19 and make the best out of this pandemic.&#13;
هدف البحث: تصف هذه الدراسة تأثيرات فيروس كورونا الجديد على عملية سلسلة التوريد لصناعة الأغذية في الدول المتقدمةمنهجية البحث: تم إجراء تحليل على 15 مقالات صناعية وتم تصنيفها إلى موضوعين رئيسيين: تأثير كل مرحلة ، والتأثيرات العامة على جميع المراحل ، وكل منها مقسم إلى مواضيع إضافية. يتم دعم المراجعة المنهجية بشكل أكبر من خلال المقابلات الشخصية مع المتخصصين في الصناعة.نتائج البحث: تُظهر النتائج أن الشركات تتجه نحو التوطين ، والتركيز على مخاطر الموردين من الدرجة الأولى ، والتجارة الإلكترونية ، وتغيير سياسات المخزون الخاصة بهم ، وتقييم مصادر التوريد البديلة لإدارة الاضطرابات التي تسببت في عملياتهم التجارية وسط تفشي COVID-19.توصيات البحث: يوصى بإيلاء المزيد من الاهتمام لحماية الإمدادات الغذائية من الاضطرابات وتعزيز تصميم سلسلة التوريد الغذائي في المستقبل. كما ينبغي تحسين المرونة في سلسلة الإمداد الغذائي في المستقبل. يمكن لشركات سلسلة التوريد استخدام الإجراءات المضادة الواردة في هذه الدراسة للتخفيف من تأثير COVID-19 وتحقيق أقصى استفادة من هذا الوباء.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر تطبيق آليات حوكمة الشركات على تحسين الآداء الوظيفى للمؤسسة دراسة تطبيقية على إحدى شركات المقاولات ( شركة ريدكون للتعمير )</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279788.html</link>
      <description>تهدف الدراسة الحالية الى إستشراف علاقة أثر تطبيق آليات حوكمة الشركات على تحسين الآداء الوظيفى للمؤسسة - دراسة تطبيقية على إحدى شركات المقاولات ( شركة ريدكون للتعمير ) وذلك من خلال عينة حصرية ومسح شامل لقيادات الشركة .حيث إعتمدت الدراسة على إستخدام أسلوب المنهج الوصفى التحليلى ، وأستخدام أداة قياس تم تطويرها للتوافق مع أهداف الدراسة وفروضها من حيث بحث علاقة أثر تطبيق آليات حوكمة الشركات على تحسين الآداء الوظيفى&amp;amp;nbsp; للمؤسسة .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;وتبين من النتائج وجود علاقة أظهرتها النتائج&amp;amp;nbsp; أن لتطبيق مبدأ التقييم&amp;amp;nbsp; ، الإنصاف والعدالة ،&amp;amp;nbsp; والشفافية ، والمساءلة ،&amp;amp;nbsp; والفعالية ، والمشاركة تساهم بشكل كبير فى تحسين آداء العمل وأن متوسط الإجابات فى كل منها يمكن إعتباره تعبير عن الرأى بالموافقة&amp;amp;nbsp; عن أن لتطبيق هذه المبادئ دور كبير جدا فى تحسين واقع العمل فى قطاع المقاولات وكان رأى المستجيبين أن تطبيق مبدأ التقييم يساهم بدرجة كبيرة جدا وبنسبة أعلى من باقى المبادىء ولكن مبدأ المشاركة يساهم&amp;amp;nbsp; بدرجة قليلة&amp;amp;nbsp; نسبيا فى تحسين الأداء الوظيفى بشركة ريدكون للتعمير ش . م . م .&#13;
The current study aims to explore the relationship of the impact of the application of corporate governance mechanisms on improving the job performance of the organization, an applied study on one of the contracting companies (Redcon Construction Company), through an exclusive sample and a comprehensive survey of the company&amp;amp;rsquo;s leaders. Where the study relied on the use of the descriptive analytical method, and the use of a measurement tool that was developed to comply with the objectives and hypotheses of the study in terms of examining the relationship of the impact of applying corporate&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; governance mechanisms on improving the functional performance of the institution.&amp;amp;nbsp; The results showed that there is a relationship shown by the results that the application of the principle of evaluation, fairness and justice, transparency, accountability, effectiveness, and participation contribute significantly to improving work performance and that the average responses in each of them can be considered an expression of opinion with approval that the application of these principles has a very big role in Improving the reality of work in the contracting sector The respondents were of the opinion that the application of the evaluation principle contributes to a very large degree and a higher percentage than the rest of the principles, but the principle of participation contributes to a relatively small degree in improving job performance in Redcon Development Company LLC.M.M&amp;amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"أثر برامج ولاء العملاء على المركز التنافسي للشركات الصناعية" "دراسة تطبيقية على الشركات العاملة في عزل الأسلاك بالورنيش"</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279790.html</link>
      <description>هدفت الدراسة إلى التعرف على أثر تصميم نظام دعم ولاء العملاء على تحسين المركز التنافسي في شركات الأسلاك النحاسية المعزولة بالورنيش في مصر، من خلال دراسة أثر أبعاد نظام دعم ولاء العملاء والمتمثلة في (سرعة الاستجابة للشكاوى، خدمات ما بعد البيع، نظام الائتمان، مكافأة العملاء، تعويض العملاء) على تحسين المركز التنافسي والمتمثل أبعاده في (التكلفة، الجودة، القيمة المدركة، الثقة).&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وقد اعتمد الباحث في تجميع البيانات على قائمة استقصاء كأداة رئيسية لجمع البيانات، وبلغ حجم مجتمع البحث المختار 150 عميل من التجار (الوسطاء) العاملين في توزيع المنتج وتم استخدام البرنامج الإحصائي SPSS كحزمة إحصائية لإدخال البيانات ومعالجتها وتحليلها.&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;The study aimed to identify the effect of developing customer loyalty system on improving the competitive position on insulated wires companies in Egypt.Through studying the effect of dimensions of customer loyalty system (fast responses for complains, after selling services, customer credit system, customer rewards and customer compensations) on improving competitive position through its dimensions (cost, quality, perceived value and trust).The researcher used the descriptive-analytical method for this purpose and relied on the survey list as the main tool for data collection. The research population consists of 150 customers of traders that work in distributing products in Egypt. The statistical package for the Statistical Analysis of Social Sciences (SPSS) was used for data entry and analysis.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Porter Diamond model to assess the impact of Public Private Partnerships on the competitiveness of Aden container terminal</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279792.html</link>
      <description>Public private partnerships (PPPs (in ports have become a means to manage port operations more effectively, and to develop new port infrastructure. In fact, they are both traditionally exclusively government functions. PPPs take more than one shape and each type is used to tackle one or more issue. This wide range of the solutions provided by the PPP makes it a desirable tool that governments are to adopt in order to overcome the shortage of resources. This research attempts to measure the impact of PPPs on enhancing the competitiveness of Aden container terminal. In addition, the research attempts to identify the present status, suggest solutions for elimination of drawbacks, and identifying reasons of inefficiency; using Diamond model for Porter during the year 2022.&#13;
أصبحت الشراكة بين القطاعين العام والخاص (PPPs) في الموانئ وسيلة أكثر فعالية لإدارة عمليات الموانئ، فضلاً عن تطوير بنية تحتية جديدة للموانئ، وعادةً ما تكون وظائف حكومية حصرية. تأخذ الشراكة بين القطاعين العام والخاص أكثر من شكل وكل نوع يستخدم لمعالجة مشكلة واحدة أو أكثر. هذه المجموعة الواسعة من الحلول التي يوفرها الشراكة بين القطاعين العام والخاص تجعلها أداة مرغوبة يجب أن تتبناها الحكومات للتغلب على نقص الموارد. يحاول البحث قياس تأثير الشراكة بين القطاعين العام والخاص في تعزيز القدرة التنافسية لمحطة حاويات عدن. بالإضافة إلى ذلك، تحديد الوضع الحالي واقتراح حلول لإزالة العيوب، وتحديد أسباب عدم الكفاءة؛ باستخدام نموذج الماسة لبورتر لعام 2022.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of Color Element of E-advertising on Social Network Platforms on sales growth</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279793.html</link>
      <description>Objective: Increased exposure on social media sites makes consumer vulnerable to digital advertising, promoting them to make a purchase. However, concentrated marketing necessitates devising innovative strategies for intriguing customers. This study assesses The impact of Color Element of E-advertising on Social Network Platforms on sales growthMethod: Descriptive analytical research design was adopted with the use of questionnaire as data collection instrument. A sample of 385 respondents was randomly selected and test instrument administered on them.Results: It showed that advertising design majorly affects the sales growth (69.6%), Conclusion: The Color used in the E-advertising on Social Network Platforms has a positive impact on sales growth.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of Design Element of E-advertising on Social Network Platforms on sales growth Mohamed Abdel Moez Aly Youssef</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279795.html</link>
      <description>Objective: Increased exposure on social media sites makes consumer vulnerable to digital advertising, promoting them to make a purchase. However, concentrated marketing necessitates devising innovative strategies for intriguing customers. This study assesses the impact of E-advertising&amp;amp;rsquo;s Design on Social Network Platforms on Sales GrowthMethod: Descriptive analytical research design was adopted with the use of questionnaire as data collection instrument. A sample of 385 respondents was randomly selected and test instrument administered on them.Results: It showed that advertising design majorly affects the sales growth (69.6%), Conclusion: The Design must be used on E-advertising on Social Network Platforms on sales growth.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تاثير الرشاقة الاستراتيجية على اداء ادارات الامن فى منظمات القطاع الخاص الدور الوسيط : لعملية ادارة المخاطر</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279804.html</link>
      <description>استهدفت هذة الدراسة معرفة تاثير الرشاقة الاستراتيجية على اداء ادارات الامن فى منظمات القطاع الخاص فى ظل وجود الدور الوسيط لعملية ادارة المخاطرحيث تم توزيع الاستبيان على عدد (400) فرداً وقام عدد (297) منهم بالرد على الاستبيان لتبلغ نسبة الاستجابة 74.3%.تم استخدام معاملى الاتساق الداخلى والفا كرونباخ لقياس ثبات الاستبيان (Cronbach&amp;amp;rsquo;s Alpha)وقد تم قياس المتغير المستقل (الرشاقة الاستراتيجية ) من خلال ابعادة (التخطيط &amp;amp;ndash; التنظيم &amp;amp;ndash; الافراد &amp;amp;ndash; التكنولوجيا الابداع &amp;amp;ndash; القدرة على استغلال الفرص ) اما المتغير التابع فقد تبنى الابعاد التالية (الحماية &amp;amp;ndash; التامين &amp;amp;ndash; الاستقرار ) حيث تم اختبار النموذج الذى يربط بين ابعاد الرشاقة الاستراتيجية مع اداء ادارات الامن فى منظمات القطاع الخاص باستخدام البرنامج الاحصائة Spss.واوضحت الدراسة وجود دلالة احصائية للابعاد الرشاقة الاستراتيجية على اداء ادارات الامن فى منظمات القطاع الخاصThis study aimed to know the impact of strategic agility on the performance of security departments in private sector organizations considering the mediating role of the risk management process. The questionnaire was distributed to (400) individuals, and (297) of them responded, with a response rate of 74.3%.The internal consistency coefficient and Cronbach's alpha were used to measure the reliability of the questionnaire (Cronbach's Alpha).The independent variable (strategic agility) was measured by dimensions (planning - organization - people - technology creativity - the ability to exploit opportunities), while the dependent variable adopted the following dimensions (protection - insurance - stability) where the model that links the dimensions of agility was tested Strategy with the performance of security departments in private sector organizations using the SPSS statistical program.The study showed that there is a statistical significance of the dimensions of strategic agility on the performance of security departments in private sector organizations.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر التوظيف الإلكتروني على الأداء الوظيفي دراسة تطبيقية على شركات مياه الشرب بجمهورية مصر العربية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279805.html</link>
      <description>هدفت هذه الدراسة إلى قياس أثر جودة التوظيف الالكتروني على الأداء الوظيفي بين العاملين بشركة مياه الشرب بالإسكندرية. وتمثلت متغيرات الدراسة في التوظيف الالكتروني متغير مستقل بأبعاده : الإستقطاب الالكتروني - الإختيار الالكتروني والتعيين الالكتروني، الاداء الوظيفي كمتغير تابع بأبعاده : الالتزام - الابداع في العمل - اداء المهامولتحقيق أغراض الدراسة تم أخذ عينة عشوائية بسيطة&amp;amp;nbsp; (ملائمة) من (505) مفردة من العاملين بشركة مياه الشرب٠ شملت رؤساء القطاعات والمديرين&amp;amp;rlm; ورؤساء الاقسام وما يعادلهم واعتمدت الدراسة على الإستبيان كأداة رئيسية لجمع البيانات ، وتم توزيع الإستبيانات على افراد العينة كما تم&amp;amp;nbsp; إجراء الإختبارات المطلوبة للتحقق من صدق وثبات أداة الدراسة ۔ولتحليل البيانات التي تم جمعها، تم استخدام عدد من الإختبارات والأساليب الأحصائية من خلال البرامج&amp;amp;nbsp; الأحصائية المتخصصة. وبناء على النتائج الإحصائية خلصت الدراسة بعدد من النتائج أهمها، وجود تأثير ودور فعال لإستراتيجية التوظيف الالكتروني على تحسين الأداء الوظيفي. وكذلك عدم وجود فروق ذات دلالة إحصائية بين متوسطات استجابات المبحوثين حول جودة التوظيف الالكتروني في تحسين الاداء الوظيفي طبقاً للمتغيرات الديموغرافية الاتية : (الفئة العمرية، المؤهل العلمي).كما اوصت الدراسة بعدد من التوصيات بناء على النتائج الإحصائية من أهمها ضرورة بطرق التوظيف الالكتروني والتي تستهدف المبادأة والإستباقية وتعزيز الإبتكار لدى العاملين بعيداً عن الروتين والرتابة والعمل التقليدي، وذلك من خلال العمل علي جذب العاملين ذوي الخبرات والقدرات والمهارات المختلفة والمتتوعة.This study aimed to measure the impact of the quality of E-recruitment on job performance among employees of the Alexandria Drinking Water Company. The study variables represented in electronic recruitment, an independent variable with its dimensions: electronic polarization - electronic selection and electronic appointment, job performance as a dependent variable with its dimensions: commitment - creativity at work - performance of tasksTo achieve the purposes of the study, a simple random sample (appropriate) was taken from (505) employees of the drinking water company, which included heads of sectors, managers, heads of departments and their equivalents. The validity and reliability of the study tool.To analyze the collected data, a number of tests and statistical methods were used through specialized statistical programs. Based on the statistical results, the study concluded with a number of results, the most important of which is the presence and effective role of the e-recruitment strategy on improving job performance. As well as the absence of statistically significant differences between the averages of the respondents' responses about the quality of electronic recruitment in improving job performance according to the following demographic variables: (age group, educational qualification).The study also recommended a number of recommendations based on statistical results, the most important of which is the necessity of electronic recruitment methods, which target initiative and proactiveness and enhance innovation among workers away from routine, monotony and traditional work, by working to attract workers with different and varied experiences, capabilities and skills.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تصميم مؤشرات الأداء المتوازن المستدام لتطوير الأداء الوظيفي والبيئي للعاملين في قطاع البترول</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279823.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;دراسة تأثير قوة مؤشرات الأداء المتوازن المستدام على الأداء الوظيفي والبيئي للعاملين بقطاع البترول، و التعرف على مدي تأثير بطاقة الأداء المتوازن على أسلوب الإدارة الاستراتيجية لقطاع البترول، والتعرف على مدى تأثير مؤشرات الأداء المتوازن المستدام على الأداء الوظيفي والبيئي، وأيضًا الدور الذى تلعبه مؤشرات الأداء المتوازن المستدام (المتغير المستقل)، الأداء البيئي (المتغير الوسيط)، الأداء الوظيفي (المتغير التابع) باستخدام معامل الارتباط البسيط في شركات قطاع البترول، و تأثير الأداء المتوازن المستدام على الأداء البيئي و الأداء الوظيفي و بحث العلاقة بين الأداء الوظيفي و الأداء البيئي بقطاع البترول .تمثل مجتمع البحث في موظفين مختلفين من عده شركات بقطاع البترول وتم أخذ عينات عشوائية من الموظفين بالشركات المختلفة بقطاع البترول والذي بلغ عددهم (300) وتم تحديد عينة عند مستوى ثقة 95 % وعند حدود خطأ معياري 5 %.ويعتمد أسلوب الدراسة الميدانية من خلال إعداد قائمة استقصاء مكونة من أربعة محاور) البيانات العامة للمستقصي &amp;amp;ndash; المتغير المستقل &amp;amp;ndash; المتغير التابع &amp;amp;ndash; المتغير الوسيط)، كل محور يتكون من مجموعة من الأسئلة، وتم توجيهها إلى مجتمع الدراسة ممن يتعاملون مع الواقع الفعلي لمشكلة الدراسة؛ بهدف التعرف على آرائهم وتحليلها فى اختبار تطبيق مؤشرات الأداء المتوازن المستدام ومتغيراته على الأداء الوظيفي وعلاقته بالأداء البيئي بالتطبيق على العاملين بالشركات المختلفة بقطاع البترول.أوضحت نتائج الدراسة بانه تم قبول جزئي للفرضيين الرئيسين الأول والثاني وقبول كلي للفرضين الرئيسين الثالث والرابع كليا، وتم اثبات صحة الفروض الفرعية.وأوصت الدراسة بمجموعة من التوصيات وعلى راسها بذل مجهود في مسار الترقيات من أجل تحقيق إرضاء العاملين بالقطاع؛ لخلق أداء وظيفي متميز يُحقق أداء بيئي يسعى إلى أداء متوازن مستدام في قطاع البترول، والعمل على ادخال تعيين جديد للسن الأصغر بالقطاع في السن تحت 30 عام للنقص في تلك الفئة العمرية بالقطاع لتحقيق الاستمرارية في نقل الخبرة والسيولة في الأداء الوظيفي مما ينعكس على الإنتاجية الكلية للقطاع.Study the impact of the strength of sustainable balanced performance indicators on the functional and environmental performance of petroleum sector workers, identify the impact of the balanced scorecard on the strategic management of the petroleum sector, identify the impact of sustainable balanced performance indicators on job and environmental performance, as well as the role played by sustainable balanced performance indicators (independent variable), environmental performance (intermediate variable), functional performance (dependent variable) using simple correlation coefficient in petroleum sector companies, and the impact of balanced sustainable performance On environmental performance and functionality and discussing the relationship between job performance and environmental performance in the oil sector.The research community represented different employees from several companies in the oil sector and random samples were taken from the employees of the various companies in the oil sector, which numbered (300) and a sample was identified at the level of confidence of 95% and at the limits of a standard error of 5%.The field study method is adopted through the preparation of a four-pronged survey list ( general data of the survey - independent variable - variable dependent - intermediate variable), each axis consists of a set of questions, and was directed to the study community who deal with the actual reality of the study problem, with the aim of identifying their opinions and analysis in testing the application of sustainable balanced performance indicators and variables on job performance and its relationship to environmental performance by applying to employees of different companies in the petroleum sector.The results of the study showed that the first and second main assumptions were partially accepted and the third and fourth presidents were fully accepted, and the sub-assumptions were proven to be valid.The study recommended a set of recommendations, led by an effort in the path of promotions in order to achieve the satisfaction of workers in the sector, to create a distinct job performance that achieves environmental performance that seeks balanced sustainable performance in the oil sector, and work to introduce a new appointment for the younger age in the sector under 30 years of age to decrease in that age group in the sector to achieve continuity in the transfer of experience and liquidity in job performance, which reflects on the overall productivity of the sector.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تأثير إدارة المعرفة في تحسين الأداء الاستراتيجي دراسة ميدانية بالتطبيق على كليات المجتمع الحكومية اليمنية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279830.html</link>
      <description>إدارة المعرفة تمثل المصدر الاستراتيجي الأكثر أهمية في بناء قدرات المنظمة الاستراتيجية، بل أصبحت العامل الأقوى والأكثر تأثيرًا وسيطرة في نجاح المنظمة أو فشلها. وهناك من يعد المعرفة عنصرًا أساسيًا من عناصر الإنتاج بالمنظمة إضافة لرأس المال والعمل، ويرى فريق آخر يتعامل مع المعرفة التي تمتلكها المنظمة على أنها تعد أصًلا رأسمالًيا يمكن أن يكون له قيمة نقدية ضمن موجودات تلك المنظمة.&amp;amp;nbsp; بالتالي تصبح إدارة المعرفة أحد الحلول الجيدة للتحديات التي تواجهها المنظمات المعاصرة، ومنها المؤسسات التعليمية وذلك لأنها المعرفة والمعلومات أصول رئيسة لا غنى عنها لهذه المؤسسات التي ينبغي أن تتعلم كيفية استثمار هذا الرصيد المعرفي بطرق جديدة، ومن ثم مشاركة هذه المعرفة داخلًيا بكفاءة وتعلم كيفية نقلها بسرعة للبيئة الخارجية من أجل التنافس وتحقيق التميز. ومما لا شك فيه أن قطاع التعليم العالي يعتبر سباًقا إلى ما توصل إليه الفكر الإداري من حيث اعتماده على إدارة المعرفة لضمان التقدم المستمر في شتى مجالات أعماله؛ وذلك لأن جودة التعليم العالي تعتمد على مدى تطبيق مدخل إدارة المعرفة وإجراءاتها وطرقها في مثل هذه المؤسسات، حيث تساعد على تحقيق كفاءة العمليات الإدارية، وجودة عملية صنع القرار، وفاعلية البرامج الاكاديمية والتدريبية. يهدف هذا البحث إلى دراسة تأثير إدارة المعرفة في تحسين مستوى الأداء الاستراتيجي في كليات المجتمع الحكومية اليمنية محل البحث، وقد طبقت على أربع كليات مجتمع حكومية يمنية (كلية المجتمع ـ صنعاء، كلية المجتمع ـ عدن، كلية المجتمع ـ عبس، كلية المجتمع ـ سيئون). جمعت البيانات الخاصة بهذا البحث بصورة أساسية عن طريق استبانة أعدت لهذا الغرض، وبلغت عدد قوائم الاستبيان الصالحة للتحليل بالنسبة للكادر الأكاديمي (240) بنسبة (85%) من إجمالي مجتمع البحث ، وبالنسبة للكادر الإداري بلغت عدد قوائم الاستبيان الصالحة للتحليل(202) بنسبة (68%) من إجمالي مجتمع البحث، وفي ضوء نتائج التحليل الإحصائي للبيانات تم الحصول على مجموعة من الاستنتاجات أهمها: فيما يتعلق بالكادر الأكاديمي، وجود تأثير إيجابي بين أبعاد إدارة المعرفة (تكنولوجيا المعلومات، الثقافة التنظيمية والقيادة التنظيمية) وبين أبعاد الأداء الاستراتيجي (منفردة ومجتمعة)، بينما لم يحقق بعد الهيكل التنظيمي هذا التأثير على (الأداء الاستراتيجي إجمالاً، بعد العملاء والعمليات الداخلية)، وفيما يتعلق بالكادر الإداري، وجود تأثير إيجابي بين أبعاد إدارة المعرفة (تكنولوجيا المعلومات، الهيكل التنظيمي والقيادة التنظيمية) وبين أبعاد الأداء الاستراتيجي (بعد العملاء، بعد العمليات الداخلية والأداء الاستراتيجي إجمالاً)، بينما لم يحقق بعد (الثقافة التنظيمية) هذا التأثير على تلك الأبعاد. وقدم الباحث مجموعة من التوصيات أهمها: ضرورة اهتمام كليات المجتمع اليمنية بامتلاك القدر الكافي من المعرفة لخلق التجانس المطلوب بين ما تمتلكه من موارد سواء كانت بشرية أم تنظيمية وبين قدراتها، من خلال المشاركة بالمعرفة مع الجامعات والمراكز البحثية، والاهتمام بالبحث والتطوير باعتباره المسار الذي يساعد على توليد معرفة جديدة لأجل خلق التجانس المطلوب؛ ضرورة المحافظة على ثقافة تنظيمية مميزة بين أفراد الكادر الأكاديمي والإداري في كليات المجتمع الحكومية اليمنية محل البحث، حيث تسهم في الترويج لنمو المعرفة من خلال التفاعل بين الادارات المختلفة وغرس الثقة فيما بينها وتعزيز الولاء للأفراد والعاملين فيها.This research aims to study the impact of knowledge management on improving the level of strategic performance in the Yemeni government community colleges, and it was applied to four Yemeni community colleges; (Sana'a Community College, Aden Community College, Abs Community College, Sayun Community College). The data for this research were mainly collected by means of a questionnaire prepared for this purpose, and the number of questionnaire lists that are valid for analysis for academic staff reached (240) at a rate of (85%) of the total research community, and for the administrative staff, the number of questionnaire lists that are valid for analysis reached (202) with a percentage of ( 68%) of the total research community. The results of the statistical analysis showed a set of conclusions the most important of which are:firstly; regard to the academic staff, there is a positive impact between the dimensions of knowledge management (information technology, organizational culture and organizational leadership) on the strategic performance dimensions generally, while the (organizational structure dimension) did not achieve this impact on (customers dimension, internal operations dimension and strategic performance in general). Secondly; regard to the administrative staff, there is a positive impact between the knowledge management dimensions (information technology, organizational structure and organizational leadership) and the strategic performance dimensions (customers dimension, internal process dimension and strategic performance generally), while (organizational culture dimension) has not achieved this impact on those dimensions. The researcher presented a set of recommendations, the most important of which are: the necessity of Yemeni community colleges&amp;amp;rsquo; interest in possessing a sufficient amount of knowledge to create the required homogeneity between their human or organizational resources and their capabilities, through sharing knowledge with universities and research centers, and interest in research and development as a path that helps to generating new knowledge in order to create the desired homogeneity; The need to maintain a distinct organizational culture among the academic and administrative staff in the Yemeni government community colleges in question, as it contributes to promoting the growth of knowledge through interaction between different departments, instilling trust among them and enhancing loyalty to individuals and their employees.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تأثير الكفاءة الجوهرية في تحسين مستوى الأداء الاستراتيجي دراسة ميدانية بالتطبيق على كليات المجتمع الحكومية اليمنية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279834.html</link>
      <description>إن الكفاءة الجوهرية نشاط تتفوق بها المنظمة على منافسيها، ويرتبط هذا النشاط بالبحث والتطوير، والبراعة التكنولوجية وتلبية رغبات العملاء، لذلك فالمقدرة المعرفية يمكن ان تستخلص من المعرفة وأساليبها في إيجاد التميز على المنافس، وطورت الأفكار الرئيسة للكفاءة الجوهرية بوساطة (Prahald&amp;amp;amp;Hamel) عن طريق سلسلة مقالات في جامعة هارفرد وأتبعوها بكتاب عن الكفاءة. وكانت أفكارهم الأساسية هي أن المنظمات يمكن أن تطور مجالات للخبرة تكون واضحة ومهمة للنمو على المدى الطويل، هذه المجالات يمكن أن تكون في أي نشاط في المنظمة وتكون مفيدة في تطوير الأنشطة المركزية والتي تضيف قيمة إلى المنتج. فالكفاءة إذًا تتمثل في قدرات الأفراد داخل المنظمة ولا شك أن هذه الكفاءات مرتبطة بوجود الأفراد فإن تركوها مؤقتًا أو بصفة دائمة فقدت معهم المنظمة تلك الكفاءات. إن هذه الكفاءة تزداد أهمية بتزايد ما يكتسبه الأفراد عن معلومات عن منظماتهم ، ومع رفع كفاءة الأفراد يصبح الأداء أفضل ، كما تتركز المهارات في الأولويات، ويعمل الجميع من أجل صالح المنظمة. العلاقة بين الكفاءات وأداء المنظمة لا تزال معضلة لم تحل، ولكن الغموض السببي فيما يتعلق بالكفاءات والأداء ضروري بين المديرين الداخليين والخارجيين من أجل ميزة تنافسية مستدامة لأنه يحد بشدة من التقليد، وبالتالي يعزز الأداء القوي. ويرى رأي آخر أن يضع قيودا على نقل هذه الكفاءات والاستفادة منها داخل المنظمة، وفي هذه الحالة، قد يؤثر على أداء المنظمة. يهدف هذا البحث إلى دراسة تأثير الكفاءة الجوهرية في تحسين مستوى الأداء الاستراتيجي في كليات المجتمع الحكومية اليمنية محل البحث، وقد طبقت على أربع كليات مجتمع حكومية يمنية (كلية المجتمع ـ صنعاء، كلية المجتمع ـ عدن، كلية المجتمع ـ عبس، كلية المجتمع ـ سيئون). جمعت البيانات الخاصة بهذا البحث بصورة أساسية عن طريق استبانة أعدت لهذا الغرض، وبلغت عدد قوائم الاستبيان الصالحة للتحليل بالنسبة للكادر الأكاديمي (240) بنسبة (85%) من إجمالي مجتمع البحث، وبالنسبة للكادر الإداري بلغت عدد قوائم الاستبيان الصالحة للتحليل (202) بنسبة (68%) من إجمالي مجتمع البحث، وفي ضوء نتائج التحليل الإحصائي للبيانات تم الحصول على مجموعة من الاستنتاجات أهمها، وجود تأثير إيجابي بين أبعاد الكفاءة الجوهرية (بعد الموارد التنظيمية، الموارد البشرية والقدرات التنظيمية) وبين أبعاد الأداء الاستراتيجي (بعد العملاء، العمليات الداخلية والنمو والتعلم) بينما لم يحقق (بعد الموارد البشرية) هذا التأثير على (الأداء الاستراتيجي إجمالاً). وقدم الباحث مجموعة من التوصيات أهمها: ضرورة تكوين فكرة عن أماكن تواجد الكفاءة الجوهرية لدى الكادر الأكاديمي والإداري في كليات المجتمع الحكومية اليمنية وتكوين مقاييس لتطوير تلك الكفاءات لدى كادر كليات المجتمع من أجل تحسين الأداء الاستراتيجي، ينبغي على كليات المجتمع اليمنية دمج الخبرة التي لديها مع المعرفة المكتسبة من الاخرين بهدف تشكيل الكفاءة الجوهرية للكادر ودمجها مع الموارد التي تمتلكها بغرض تحسين الأداء استراتيجي للأمد الطويل.&#13;
&amp;amp;nbsp; Research aims to study the impact of core competency on improving the level of strategic performance in the Yemeni government community colleges, and it was applied to four Yemeni community colleges; (Sana'a Community College, Aden Community College, Abs Community College, Sayun Community College). The data for this research were mainly collected by means of a questionnaire prepared for this purpose, and the number of questionnaire lists that are valid for analysis for academic staff reached (240) at a rate of (85%) of the total research community, and for the administrative staff, the number of questionnaire lists that are valid for analysis reached (202) with a percentage of ( 68%) of the total research community. The results of the statistical analysis showed a set of conclusions the most important of which are there is a positive impact between core competency dimensions (organizational resources, human resources, and organizational capabilities) and strategic performance dimensions (customer dimension, internal processes dimension, and the growth and learning dimension), but the )human resources dimension( did not have this impact on the strategic performance generally. The researcher presented a set of recommendations, the most important of which are: It is necessary to form an idea about the locations of the core competency of the academic and administrative staff in the Yemeni government community colleges, and to form measures to develop these competencies among the community college staff in order to improve strategic performance,Yemeni community colleges should integrate the experience they have with the knowledge gained from others with the aim of forming the core competency of its employees and integrating it with the resources it possesses to create an efficiency that contributes to achieving long-term strategic performance.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>قياس تطبيقات الموانىء الذكية في محطة حاويات ميناء عدن</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_279836.html</link>
      <description>شهد النصف الثاني من القرن العشرين نموًا متزايدًا في الدور الذي تؤديه الموانئ في التبادل التجاريّ بين الدول وبعضها البعض؛ وذلك بسبب كونها نقطة إلتقاء بين مراكز الإنتاج والاستهلاك، وانتقلت الموانئ من مجرد محطات مائية لاستقبال السفن إلى صناعة عالمية متشابكة ومعقدة؛ تتداخل فيها الإستثمارات المالية بالتطورات التكنولوجية، وتوجهت الدول لتطوير موانئها لتعزيز قدراتها التنافسية. ومن أهم التحديات التي تواجه النقل البحريّ إحتدام حدة المنافسة إقليميًا وعالميًا في مجال صناعة النقل البحريّ على ضوء التغيرات السياسية والإقتصادية، لذلك يجب على متخذي القرار رفع كفاءة البنية التحتية وتطويرها (قردش، 2021). هدفت الدراسة إلي معرفة محددات الأداء التنافسي لمحطة حاويات ميناء عدن، وكذلك التعرف على المتطلبات الضرورية لإنجاح تطبيق مفهوم الموانئ الذكية بالمحطة وتقديم مجموعة من المقترحات والتي من الممكن الإستفادة منها في الإهتمام بتطبيق مفهوم الموانئ الذكية بالمحطة وذلك خلال العام 2022. قامت الدراسة بوضع بعض التوصيات والتي من شأنها زيادة القدرة التنافسية لمحطة حاويات ميناء عدن وقاموا بوضع مقترح زمني لمراحل تنفيذ إسترتيجية لتحويل ميناء عدن لميناء ذكي.The second half of the twentieth century witnessed a significant growth in the role played by ports in the trade exchange between countries and each other, due to the point of trade exchange and investments to enhance its competitive capabilities. One of the most important challenges facing maritime transport is the intense regional and global competition in the field of maritime transport industry for driving and economy; therefor, decision makers should raise the efficiency of their infrastructure and develop it. The study aimed to know the determinants of the competitive performance of the Aden container terminal, as well as to identify the necessary requirements for the successful implementation of the concept of smart ports in Aden terminal, and to present a set of proposals and recommendations that can be benefited from in the interest in implementing the concept of smart ports during the year 2022. The study made some recommendations that would increasing the competitiveness of Aden container terminal; they developed a timetable proposal for the implementation stages of the strategy of transforming the port of Aden into a smart port.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>اثر كفاءة سوق رأس المال على العائد السوقي للاسهم دراسة مقارنة بين البورصة المصرية وسوق دبى المالى</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280000.html</link>
      <description>هدفت الدراسة الى قياس كفاءة سوق المال فى البورصة المصرية وسوق دبى المالى وبيان تاثير ذلك على العائد السوقى للاسهم المقيدة فى سوق المال ، حيث تتلخص اشكالية الدراسة فى الاجابة على تساؤل هو هل تؤثر كفاءة سوق رأس المال على القيمة السوقية للسهم المدرجة فى البورصة المصرية وسوق المال فى دبى ؟، عدد (205 شركة) مدرجة تمثل عدد (18 قطاع) ، باختلاف نوع الصناعة والخدمة المقدمة ، مابين قطاعات مالية وقطاعات غير مالية ، ويضم سوق دبى المالى عدد (64 شركة) مدرجة تمثل عدد (11 قطاع ) ، خلال الفترة من 2017-2021م ، وتوصلت نتائج الدراسة الى مؤشرات كفاءة سوق رأس المال تؤثر على العائد السوقى للاسهم فى البورصة المصرية بنسبة 58.7%&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; و تؤثر على العائد السوقى للاسهم فى سوف دبى&amp;amp;nbsp; بنسبة&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 65.2% ، ، وتؤثر على العائد السوقى للاسهم فى المجتمع ككل بنسبة 59.33% ، واوصت الدراسة بان تهتم ادارة البورصة المصرية بتحسين مستوى كفاءة سوق رأس المال بالاخص فيما يتعلق بزيادة معدلات السيولة.The Study Aimed To Measure The Efficiency Of The Capital Market In The Egyptian Stock Exchange And The Dubai Financial Market And To Show The Impact Of This On The Market Return Of The Shares Listed In The Money Market. In Dubai?, There Are (205) Listed Companies Representing (18 Sectors), According To The Type Of Industry And The Service Provided, Between Financial And Non-Financial Sectors. The Dubai Financial Market Includes (64) Listed Companies Representing (11 Sectors), During The Period From 2017-2021 AD, And The Results Of The Study Found Indicators Of Capital Market Efficiency That Affect The Market Return Of Shares In The Egyptian Stock Exchange By 58.7% And Affect The Market Return Of Shares In Dubai By 65.2%, And Affect The Market Return Of Shares In Society As A Whole By 59.33% , The Study Recommended That The Egyptian Stock Exchange Management Pay Attention To Improving The Efficiency Of The Capital Market, Especially With Regard To Increasing Liquidity Rates.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تقييم المزيج التسويقي المستدام في قطاع الثروة السمكية بالتطبيق على المعهد القومي لعلوم البحار والمصايد</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280001.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;تهدف الدراسة إلى اختبار وجود ارتباط بين المزيج التسويقي المستدام والتنمية المستدامة لقطاع الثروة السمكية باعتبارها احد قضايا العصر فى الدول النامية وإلقاء الضوء على موضوع التنمية الذى أصبح من أكثر القضايا الدولية إلحاحاً في الوقت الراهن خاصة مع زيادة حدة التنافس فى الأسواق سواء المحلية او العالمية&amp;amp;nbsp; ، ومن هنا جاءت أهمية التسويق كأداة فعالة من خلال وظائفها فى دعم عملية التنمية ودفعها من خلال تحقيق أهداف تساعد على جذب الاستثمارات المباشرة والغير مباشرة من خلال تنفيذ مشاريع حيوية وإدخال تكنولوجية حديثة .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; ان الثروة السمكية فى مصر لها مميزاتها وخصائصها الجيدة ولكن لا تحظى بالعرض والاستغلال الجيد الذي يؤهلها للمنافسة فى الأسواق العالمية او المحلية، وقد يرجع ذلك الى قله الخبرة لاستغلال هذه الثروة السمكية بالإضافة الى عدم وجود خطة تسويقية تساعد على تسويق والاستغلال الجيد لهذه الثروة لذلك جاء هذه الفكرة البحثية.The study aims to test the existence of a link between the sustainable marketing mix and the sustainable development of the fisheries sector as one of the issues of the times in developing countries and to shed light on the issue of development, which has become one of the most pressing international issues at the present time, especially with the increase in the intensity of competition in the local or global markets.&amp;amp;nbsp; Here came the importance of marketing as an effective tool through its functions in supporting and pushing the development process through achieving goals that help attract direct and indirect investments through the implementation of vital projects and the introduction of modern technology.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The fish wealth in Egypt has its advantages and good characteristics, but it does not have a good supply and exploitation that qualifies it to compete in the global or local markets, and this may be due to the lack of experience to exploit this fish wealth in addition to the lack of a marketing plan that helps in marketing and making good use of this wealth. From here&amp;amp;nbsp; This research idea came up.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دورأخلاقيات الإدارة في تحسين الأداء الوظيفى داخل الجمعيات الخيرية بجمهورية مصر العربية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280002.html</link>
      <description>نظراً للوجه الحديث للمفاهيم التي لها علاقة بسبب الانهيار الذي يحدث في عالم المال والأعمال وهي الأخلاق، حاولنا من خلال هذه الدراسة إثبات وجود هذا المفهوم ودرجة تأثيره في المنظمة بصفة عامة، إذ هو لصيق بالعنصر البشري الذي يعتبر كدعامة أساسية لتطور ونمو المنظمة هذا ما ينعكس بصفة خاصة على أدائه وقيامه بالأعمال الموكلة له وهذا ما يدخل تحت مسمى الأداء الوظيفي.ولتبيان ذلك أكثر حاولنا إسقاط هذه المفاهيم على أرض الواقع من خلال الدراسة الميدانية التي قمنا بها ، ومن أجل تحقيق ذلك تم الاعتماد على المنهج الوصفي التحليلي، كما اعتمد الباحث &amp;amp;nbsp;على تحليل البيانات على أساليب الإحصاء الوصفي باستخدام برنامج (SPSS) إذ تجلى بوضوح مدى ارتباط أخلاقيات الإدارة بتحسين الأداء ، حيث طبيعة العلاقة كانت طردية.Owing to the modern perceptions of concepts related to the collapse taking place in finance and business field, which is &amp;amp;ldquo;Ethics&amp;amp;rdquo;, we tried through this thesis to establish the existence of this concept and its degree of impact on organization in general. Such concept is, closely, related to the humans, which is considered fundamental pillar for the development and growth of the organization. This is particularly reflected in its performance and carrying out businesses entrusted thereto, which is included under &amp;amp;ldquo;Functionality&amp;amp;rdquo;.To further clarify this, we tried to apply such concepts on the ground through the field study we carried out. To achieve the same, we have relied on the descriptive analysis approach. Moreover, the Researcher relied on the data analysis though the descriptive statistics, using the SPSS programs, which clearly demonstrated the extent to which management ethics are linked and concerned with improving the performance, as the nature of the relationship was positive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تأثير التمكين على الاستغراق الوظيفي بالتطبيق على المستشفيات الجامعية في جمهورية مصر العربية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280003.html</link>
      <description>هدفت هذه الدراسة إلى قياس تأثير التمكين على الاستغراق الوظيفي بالتطبيـق علـى المستشفيات الجامعية في مصــر، وتكون مجتمع البحث من مستشفيات جامعة (المنصورة, الزقازيق, جامعة قناة السويس), وتم جمع البيانات من 375 مفردة من (الفريق الطبي, الفنيون, والإداريون).&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وتوصلت الدراسة إلى وجود تأثير معنوي للتمكين على أحد أبعاد الاستغراق الوظيفي المتمثل في (الاستغراق الادراكي)، بينما توصلت إلى عدم وجود تأثير معنوي للتمكين على أبعاد الاستغراق الوظيفي المتمثله في (الاستغراق الشعوري، الاستغراق الجسدي) في المستشفيات محل الدراسة، وتوصلت الدراسة إلى عدة توصيات منها ( تمكين العاملين بالقدر الذي يمنحهم القدرة على الإهتمام بالمرضى، وتكوين قيادات صف ثاني قادره على قيادة المستشفي في مختلف المستويات الإدارية، يجب منح العاملين صلاحيات إتخاذ قرارات تتعلق بالعمل، ضرورة توعية القيادات والعاملين بالمستشفيات الجامعية بأهمية التمكين لما له من تأثير كبير على زيادة الاستغراق الوظيفي للعاملين وبالتالي تحسين الخدمات الصحية المقدمة للمرضي.This study aimed to measure the impact of empowerment on job involvement by applying it to university hospitals in Egypt. And The research community consisted of University hospitals (Mansoura, Zagazig, Suez Canal University), and data were collected from 375 individuals (medical team, technicians, and administrators).&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study concluded that there was a significant impact of empowerment on one of the dimensions of &amp;amp;nbsp;job involvement &amp;amp;nbsp;represented in (cognitive involvement), while it concluded that there was no significant impact of empowerment on the dimensions of job involvement represented in (emotional involvement, physical involvement) in the hospitals under study, and the study reached several recommendations Including (empowering workers to the extent that gives them the ability to take care of patients, and the formation of second-class leaders capable of leading the hospital at various administrative levels, workers must be given the powers to make work-related decisions, the need to educate leaders and workers in university hospitals about the importance of empowerment because of its great impact on increasing the job involvement employees, thus improving health services provided to patients.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Air transportation between climate change and carbon emissions (Case study: Borg El Arab airport, Egypt)</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280004.html</link>
      <description>أحد أهداف الاستدامة البيئية هو الإهتمام بالبيئة، والإستدامة البيئية تعني أنها قدرة البيئة على الإستمرار في العمل بشكل صحيح. لذلك، فإن الهدف من الإستدامة البيئية هو تقليل التدهور البيئي، والإستدامة تتطلب تغذيتها بشكل طبيعي، مما يعني أن الطبيعة قادرة على تجديد التوازن البيئي، ويمكن تحقيق ذلك من خلال دمج الإعتبارات البيئية عند التخطيط للتنمية حتى لا تتلف رأس المال الطبيعي كحد أدنى.الغرض من هذه الدراسة هو تقليل انبعاثات الكربون في المطارات المصرية، دراسة حالة مطار برج العرب، مصر.&#13;
One of the goals of environmental sustainability is the concern for the environment, and environmental sustainability means that it is the ability of the environment to continue to function properly. Therefore, the goal of environmental sustainability is to minimize environmental degradation, and sustainability requires nourishing it naturally, meaning that nature is able to renew the ecological balance, this can be achieved by incorporating environmental considerations when planning development so as not to damage the natural capital, as a minimum.The purpose of this research is to reduce carbon emissions in the Egyptian airports, case study: Borg El Arab airport, Egypt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور الثورة الصناعية الرابعة في التطوير الإداري لأندية الرياضية بالمملكة العربية السعودية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280005.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث إلى دراسة تطوير المؤسسات الرياضية بالمملكة العربية السعودية باستخدام الثورة الصناعية الرابعة وهي (الذكاء الاصطناعي &amp;amp;ndash; الروبوت ) وقد استخدمت الباحثة المنهج الوصفي وقامت الباحثة بتصميم استمارة استبيان كأداة من أدوات جمع البيانات وبعد تقنتين الاستبيان من حيث الصدق والثبات ، وتم تطبيقه على (50) مفردة من المدراء والإداريين في الأندية الرياضية واستخدمت المعالجات الإحصائية في تحليل البيانات المتعلقة بالبحث وأسفر تطبيق الاستبيان عن الوصول إلى عدد من النتائج تمثلت في اجماع عينة الدراسة تجاه مبررات استخدام تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة بالمجال الرياضي كان بدرجة موافق وبقيمة المتوسط الحسابي العام للمحور تساوي(2.71)وبنسبة مئوية (0.3) ، وبينما كانت مميزاتها بدرجة موافق وبقيمة المتوسط الحسابي العام للمحور تساوي (2.59)وبنسبة مئوية( 0.3 )، وكانت اهم متطلباتها بدرجة موافق بقيمة المتوسط الحسابي العام للمحور تساوي(2.59) وبنسبة مئوية (0.5)، وحصلت معوقاتها بدرجة موافق وبقيمة المتوسط الحسابي العام للمحور تساوي(2.52)وبنسبة مئوية (0.5).وتوصل البحث الى عدد من الاستنتاجات من أهمها الاعتماد على الذات لرفع مستوى المعيشة في جانب مبررات استخدام تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة بالمجال الرياضي ، وكانت عبارة تواكب المؤسسات الرياضية التي تعمل في المجال الرياضي التطورات المتسارعة لوسائل وأساليب التواصل الالكترونية وما تتسم به من سهولة وبساطة في جانب مميزات تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة بالمجال الرياضي ، وكانت عبارة المعرفة الكافية لاستخدام تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة في جانب متطلبات تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة بالأندية الرياضية ، وكانت عبارة معوقات استخدام تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة في الأداء الإداري غير فعال في المجال الرياضي في جانب معوقات تطبيقات الثورة الصناعية الرابعة بالأندية الرياضية .&amp;amp;nbsp;وفي ضوء النتائج تم وضع مجموعة من التوصيات من أهمها: توجيه وزارة الرياضة لتضمين برامج تدريب الكوادر الإدارية بالأندية الرياضية بموضوعات تتعلق بالثورة الصناعية الرابعة وتطبيقاتها في المجال الرياضي وإجراء دراسات معمقة حول مستقبل الخطط التنموية للأندية الرياضية وموائمتها لتوجه المملكة 2030 لتمكين الإداريين بمفاهيم الثورة الصناعية الرابعة.The Research Aims To Study The Development Of Sports Institutions, In The Kingdom Of Saudi Arabia, Using The Fourth Industrial Revolution, Which Is (Artificial Intelligence - Robot). And It Was Applied To (50) Individuals, From Managers And Administrators In Sports Clubs, And Statistical Treatments Were Used To Analyze The Data Related To The Research. It Was In Agreement With The General Arithmetic Mean Value Of The Axis Equal To (2.71) And With A Percentage Of (0.3), And While Its Features Were In Agreement, And With The Value Of The General Arithmetic Mean Of The Axis Equal To (2.59) And With A Percentage Of (0.3), And Its Most Important Requirements Were With A Degree Of Agreement With The Value Of The General Arithmetic Average For The Axis It Is Equal To (2.59) With A Percentage Of (0.5), And Its Obstacles Were Obtained With A Degree Of Agreement And The Value Of The General Arithmetic Mean For The Axis Is Equal To (2.52) And With A Percentage (0.5).The Research Reached A Number Of Conclusions, The Most Important Of Which Is Self-Reliance To Raise The Standard Of Living In Addition To The Justifications For Using The Applications Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution In The Sports Field. A Phrase That Keeps Pace With Sports Institutions Working In The Sports Field, The Rapid Developments Of Electronic Means And Methods Of Communication, And Its Ease And Simplicity On The Side Of The Advantages Of The Applications Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution In The Sports Field, And The Phrase Sufficient Knowledge To Use The Applications Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution, On The Side Of The Requirements Of The Applications Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution In Sports Clubs, And The Phrase &amp;amp;ldquo;Obstacles Of Using The Applications Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution, In Administrative Performance Is Ineffective In The Sports Field, On The Side Obstacles To The Applications Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution In Sports Clubs.In Light Of The Results, A Set Of Recommendations Were Developed, The Most Important Of Which Are: Directing The Ministry Of Sports To Include Training Programs For Administrative Cadres In Sports Clubs, On Topics Related To The Fourth Industrial Revolution And Its Applications In The Sports Field, And Conducting In-Depth Studies On The Future Of Development Plans For Sports Clubs, And Their Alignment With The Kingdom&amp;amp;rsquo;s 2030 Orientation, To Empower Administrators Concepts Of The Fourth Industrial Revolution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر تطبيق مفهوم الموانئ الذكية على استدامة سلسلة التوريد (دراسة حالة: المنطقة الحرة بمصراته - دولة ليبيا)</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280006.html</link>
      <description>مع تطور صناعة السفن بصفة عامة وتسارع صناعة النقل البحري بصفة خاصة؛ أدي ذلك لتزايد دور الموانئ في الاعتماد على التقنيات الذكية بشكل كبير، إلا أن الموانئ قد واجهت العديد من التغيرات التي دعت الى أهمية استدامة سلاسل التوريد، وظهرت مفاهيم حديثة في إدارة الموارد التي من خلالها يتم تحسين مستوى الأداء لتحقيق هدف البقاء والاستمرار في ظل عالم تنافسي، وتبني مفاهيم إدارية حديثة تمكن المنظمة من التعامل مع التحديات التي تواجهها والتغلب عليها لتحقيق مستوى أداء أفضل.تهدف هذه الدراسة الى التعرف على تأثير تطبيق متطلبات التحول إلى مفهوم الميناء الذكي بالمنطقة الحرة بمصراته في دولة ليبيا، وذلك لدراسة وتوضيح المعايير المطلوب تطبيقها للتحول إلى الموانئ الذكية وكيفية تطبيقها في المنطقة الحرة بمصراته. وذلك من أجل تحسين أداء الاستدامة بالمواكبة مع تطبيق متطلبات التحول الرقمي والاتجاه نحول الميناء الذكي للمنطقة الحرة بمدينة مصراتة؛ خلال العام 2022.With the development of ship industry in general and the acceleration of shipping industry in particular; which led to increasing the role of ports in relying on smart technologies significantly, but the ports have faced many changes that called for the importance of the sustainability of supply chains, and modern concepts have emerged in resource management through which the level of performance is improved to achieve the goal of survival and continuity in a competitive world, and the adoption of Modern management concepts that enable the organization to deal with the challenges it faces and overcome them to achieve a better level of performance.This research aims to identify the impact of the requirements of the transition to the concept of the smart port in the Misurata free zone in the State of Libya, in order to study and clarify the criteria required to be applied for the transition to smart ports and how to apply them in the free zone in Misurata. In order to improve the performance of sustainability in line with the application of the requirements of digital transformation and the tendency to transform the smart port of the free zone in the city of Misurata; During the year 2022.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور الترويج الإلكتروني للبحوث العلمية في تحقيق الميزة التنافسية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280010.html</link>
      <description>تم في هذا البحث دراسة دور الترويج الإلكتروني للبحوث العلمية في تحقيق الميزة التنافسية في جامعه حلوان من وجهه نظر اعضاء هيئات التدريس والجهة المعاونة ، حيث تناول عناصر الترويج الالكتروني الرئيسية ( الإعلان الالكتروني ، العلاقات العامة الإلكترونية ، تنشيط المبيعات ، التسويق الإلكتروني المباشر ) ، بالإضافة إلى أدوات الترويج الإلكتروني (&amp;amp;nbsp; الترويج عبر المواقع الالكترونية ، الترويج محركات البحث ، الترويج عبر البريد الالكتروني ، الترويج عبر الفهارس ، الترويج عبر الهواتف المحمولة ) .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; هذا بجانب دراسة الميزة التنافسية من حيث مفهومها ، الاهداف ، الاهمية ، ابعادها ، مصادرها ، خصائص الميزة التنافسية ، استراتيجيات الميزة التنافسية ، خطوات تحقيق الميزة التنافسية ، معوقات تحقيق الميزة التنافسية .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;وقد تم استخدام المنهج الوصفي التحليلي في الوصول الي نتائج البحث ، حيث تم اعداد الاستبانة لجمع البيانات من مفردات مجتمع البحث ، من خلال عينة طبقية عشوائية من اعضاء هيئات التدريس والجهة المعاونة بلغت (384) مفردة ، تم استرداد ( 367) استبانة منها ، حيث استبعدت (7) منها لأنها لم تحقق الشروط المطلوبة ، وذلك للحصول علي تصور كامل ودقيق حول موضوع البحث ، وبالتالي فإن عدد الاستبيانات التي خضعت للتحليل الاحصائي بلغت ( 360) استبانة بنسبة 93.75%.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وقد تم التوصل الي مجموعه من النتائج من اهمها : ان هناك دور لعناصر الترويج الالكتروني ( الإعلان الالكتروني ، العلاقات العامة الإلكترونية ، تنشيط المبيعات ، التسويق الإلكتروني المباشر ) في تحقيق الميزة التنافسية ، ان هناك دور " التكلفة ، السرعة ، الجودة " في تحقيق الميزة التنافسية لجامعه حلوان ، توجد فروق في استجابات حول دور الترويج الإلكتروني للبحوث العلمية في تحقيق الميزة التنافسية في جامعه حلوان تعزي لبعض المتغيرات الديمغرافية ( الجنس ، سنوات الخبرة ، الدرجة العلمية ) .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وتم تقديم مجموعه من التوصيات ، كان من ابرازها : الاهتمام بالترويج الالكتروني لدوره في مواكبة التغيرات في احتياجات ورغبات العملاء ، مواكبة وسائل تنشيط المبيعات الالكترونية وتسهيل استقطاب عملاء جدد من خلال الحوافز التشجيعية المبتكرة مثل " الكتالوجات ،&amp;amp;nbsp; هدايا ، كوبونات الخصم "&amp;amp;nbsp; ، الحفاظ علي ادوات الترويج المتعلقة بالمواقع الاجتماعية ، تفعيل استخدام البريد الالكتروني في الترويج للخدمات البحثية لجامعه حلوان .&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp; In this research, the role of electronic promotion of scientific research in achieving the competitive advantage at Helwan University was studied from the point of view of faculty members and the supporting agency. Electronic promotion tools (promotion via websites, promotion through search engines, promotion via e-mail, promotion through indexes, promotion via mobile phones).&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; This is in addition to studying competitive advantage in terms of its concept, goals, importance, dimensions, sources, characteristics of competitive advantage, strategies for competitive advantage, steps to achieve competitive advantage, and obstacles to achieving competitive advantage.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The analytical descriptive approach was used to reach the results of the research, where the questionnaire was prepared to collect data from the vocabulary of the research community, through a stratified random sample of faculty members and the supporting agency amounted to (384) items, (367) questionnaires were retrieved from them, as they were excluded (7) of them because they did not meet the required conditions, in order to obtain a complete and accurate perception of the subject of the research, and therefore the number of questionnaires that were subjected to statistical analysis amounted to (360) questionnaires, with a rate of 93.75%.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; A set of results has been reached, the most important of which are: There is a role for the elements of electronic promotion (electronic advertising, electronic public relations, sales promotion, direct electronic marketing) in achieving the competitive advantage, that there is a role of "cost, speed, quality" in achieving the competitive advantage. For Helwan University, there are differences in the respondents' responses about the role of electronic promotion of scientific research in achieving competitive advantage at Helwan University due to some demographic variables (gender, years of experience, academic degree).&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; A set of recommendations were presented, the most prominent of which were: Paying attention to electronic promotion and its role in keeping pace with changes in the needs and desires of customers, keeping pace with means of stimulating electronic sales and facilitating attracting new customers through innovative incentives such as "catalogues, gifts, discount coupons", maintaining promotional tools Related to social sites, activating the use of e-mail in promoting the research services of Helwan University.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية والثقة في توسط العلاقة بين خلق القيمة والنوايا السلوكية للعميل</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280012.html</link>
      <description>سعت هذه الدراسة إلى التعرف على دور الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية والثقة في توسط العلاقة بين خلق القيمة والنوايا السلوكية للعميل&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; سؤال البحث 1: هل توجد علاقة إيجابية ذات دلالة بين خلق القيمة والنوايا السلوكية للعميل؟&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; سؤال البحث 2: هل توجد علاقة إيجابية ذات دلالة إحصائية بين من خلال الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية؟&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; كانت العينة المستهدفة للدراسة عبارة عن مشترين لمنتجات وخدمات باهظت الثمن. تم اختيار عينة من 111 فرد. تم إجراء الاستطلاع من خلال استطلاع عبر البريد الإلكتروني او ارسال رابط الاستبيان تتم إدارته ذاتيًا.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; طُلب من المستجيبين استخدام مقياس من نوع Likert يتراوح من 1 إلى 7 للإشارة الى مستويات موافق بشدة ف استبيان تم تطويره من خلال مراجعة شاملة للأدبيات بالإضافة إلى الإحصاءات الوصفية مثل التكرار والمتوسط ​​والمعيار الانحراف ومعامل الاختلاف، وتحليل عامل التأكيد وتم استخدام تحليل الانحدار المتعدد لاختبار اثنين من المقترحات الرئيسية واثبات الفرضيات التالية:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; الفرضية 1: توجد علاقة إيجابية ذات دلالة إحصائية على العلاقة بين القيمة الوظيفية والنوايا السلوكية للعميل من خلال الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; الفرضية 2: توجد علاقة إيجابية ذات دلالة إحصائية على العلاقة بين قيمة التجربة والنوايا السلوكية للعميل من خلال الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; الفرضية 3: توجد علاقة إيجابية ذات دلالة إحصائية على العلاقة بين القيمة الرمزية والنوايا السلوكية للعميل من خلال الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; الفرضية 4: توجد علاقة إيجابية ذات دلالة إحصائية على العلاقة بين التكلفة والنوايا السلوكية للعميل من خلال الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية. فيما يلي مناقشة شاملة لنتائج اختبار الفرضيات.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وجدت هذه الدراسة ان هناك تأثير مباشر بين خلق القيمة المتمثلة في أربع عناصر محددة في القيمة الوظيفية، قيمة التجربة والتكلفة على النوايا السلوكية للعميلكما انه ليس للقيمة الرمزية التي تشير لتحقيق الذات او الشعور بالرضا عن النفس وانعكاس الشخصية أي تأثير على النوايا السلوكية للعميل لاكن تم ملاحظة ان معظم المشترين للسلع او الخدمات الفاخرة يميلون لمثل هذه المنتجات للتعبير عن المكانة الاجتماعية.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; تعتبر الصورة الذهنية للعلامة التجارية عامل مؤثر ومهم يتوسط العلاقة بين محددات خلق القيمة والنوايا السلوكية للعميل وتعتبر العلامة التجارية مصدر لتوجه العميل نحو الشراء الاستمرارية في التعامل وبالأخص انها تقدم قيمة مقابل المال&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; تم التوصل الى ان الثقة ليست بعامل مؤثر بشكل قوي وانه عامل يؤثر في العلاقة بعد التوجه لعملية الشراء عامل التكلفة قد يكون مؤثر لاعب أساسي في العلاقة إذا تعدى مستويات معينة تعتبر حدود للعميل.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; المكانة الاجتماعية عامل مهم جدا ومؤثر في حالة المنتجات الفاخرة باهظت الثمن&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; أخيرا التجربة وتكرار العملية عامل مهم يحدد ما إذا كان العميل سيعيد عملية الشراء ام لا. Introduction:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The value creation process is a complex, accurate and important process for marketers, especially when introducing a new product or service.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; This study aims to study the impact of value creation on behavioral intentions and the role of both the brand image and trust, as the brand image and the process of building trust for the customer are among the important things that achieve the goals of the organizations, which is one of their most important interests is to maintain a relationship with the customer and win new customers Study problem:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; It became clear from the review of previous studies that there are shortage in these studies in general and in Egypt in particular with regard to the issue of value creation and its relationship to behavioral intentions, at the level of companies in different fields, in addition to that there are not enough studies that provide a theoretical or practical model for the relationship between customer value creation and behavioral intentions And the role of&amp;amp;nbsp; both brand image and trust in this effect&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The main question is "The role of brand image and trust in mediating the relationship between value creation and customer behavioral intentions"&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Study questions:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The main question: Is there an effect of the brand image on the relationship between customer value creation and the behavioral intentions in the presence of trust?&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The first question: Is there a statistically significant positive relationship on the relationship between functional value and the customer's behavioral intentions through the brand image?&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The second question: Is there a positive relationship with statistical significance on the relationship between the hedonic value and the customer behavioral intentions through the brand image?&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The third question: Is there a statistically significant positive relationship on the relationship between the symbolic value and the behavioral intentions of through the brand image?&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;The fourth question: Is there a positive relationship with statistical significance on the relationship between the cost and the behavioral intentions through the brand image? Research design and methodology:1- Research design&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; This study is descriptive research that uses the survey for the purpose to describe the characteristics of a population, the process is to determine the answer to the questions of who, what, where, how and when.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The end result is a realistic, accurate and useful systematic description of the statistical calculations. (Sekaran, 2003).2- Samples plan:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The sample is defined as a subset of the population from which the researcher can draw conclusions about the population (Sekaran, 2003). The sampling plan defines the methods and procedures for taking targeted samples.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; (Davis, 2005) proposed a seven-step sampling process to avoid sampling errors and to ensure statistical and sample efficiency.3- Study population:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The target community is the people who buy or use luxury products or services in Egypt.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; There were five-star hotels and luxury cars or cosmetics.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study focuses on a specific segment of what they buy to measure the customer's value creation and behavioral intentions, the researcher decided to limit the scope of the research to three products&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - High-priced cars represented in Mercedes, BMW and Audi&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - Five-star hotels represented by Four Seasons, Movenpick and Radisson Blue&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - Skin care products represented by La Roche-Posay, Bio derma and Nuxe&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The selection of this sample is justified by the following:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 1- These products or services provided by hotels are the most common and famous.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; 2- The field of work of the researcher in car marketing.4- Sample size:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Sample size is an important consideration. Sekaran (2003) mentioned two determinants of sample size: accuracy and confidence. Accuracy is a function of the extent of variance in the sampling distribution of the sample mean and confidence is the factor of certainty that estimates made by the researcher will be true of the population. In business research, a confidence level of 95% is acceptable. Yamane (1967) provides a simplified formula for calculating sample size. A 95% confidence level is assumed and P = 0.5n =N/ [(1+N) e&amp;amp;sup2;]n is sampleN is populatione&amp;amp;sup2; is probability of error5- Data collection mechanism:&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The tool used in this research is the electronic questionnaire by sending the link to the buyers.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; the justification for use and design of the questionnaire, element formatting, and visual appearance.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; Modification and ethics involved in survey processes are discussed below.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The cover letter precedes of the questionnaire package with information about the purpose of the survey, the request for assistance, and an assurance of confidentiality. For this research, four sections were included in the questionnaire.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The period to collect data is 6 months, from 12/2021 to 05/2022.6- Results&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - This study found that there is a direct effect between value creation represented by three specific elements in functional, experience and cost value on customer behavioral intentions.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - Also, the symbolic value that refers to self-satisfaction and reflection of personality haven&amp;amp;rsquo;t any effect on the behavioral intentions of the customer, but it has been noted that most buyers of luxury products or services tend to luxury products to express social status.&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;- The brand image is an influential and important factor that mediates the relationship between the determinants of value creation and the behavioral intentions of the customer.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - the trust is not a strongly influencing factor, and that it is a factor that affects the relationship after going to the purchase process.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - The cost factor may be influential and a key player in the relationship if it exceeds certain levels that are considered limits for the customer.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - Social status is a very important and influential factor in the case of luxury products.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; - Finally, experience and repetition of the process is an important factor that determines whether the customer will return the purchase or not.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>العلاقة بين تكامل انظمة المعلومات وجوده القرار الإداري دراسة تطبيقيه على جامعة حلوان</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280014.html</link>
      <description>هدفت الدراسة إلى التعرف على العلاقة بين تكامل أنظمة المعلومات وجودة القرار الإداري بجامعة حلوان، واعتمد الباحث في الدراسة على تقييم تكامل نظم معلومات وجودة القرار الإداري من خلال استبيان تم توزيعه إلكترونيا وكانت الاستجابة من 145 من العاملين في مجال تكنولوجيا المعلومات بالجامعة والقائمين على اتخاذ القرار في الجامعة على جميع المستويات الإدارية؛ وقد تم تحليل هذه البيانات الإحصائية من خلال برنامج spss&amp;amp;nbsp; بالاعتماد علي عدد من الأدوات الإحصائية (الوسط الحسابي، المتوسط الحسابي، الانحراف المعياري،&amp;amp;nbsp; معامل الارتباط).The Study Aimed to Identify the Relationship between the Integration of Information Systems and the Quality of Administrative Decision at Helwan University and The Researcher Relied in the Study on the Evaluation of the Integration of Information Systems and the Quality of the Administrative Decision through A Questionnaire Distributed Electronically and the Response was From 145 Workers in the Field of Information Technology at the University and Decision-Makers at the University at all Administrative Levels. These Statistical Data were Analyzed Through the spss Program Based on a Number of Statistical Tools (Arithmetic Mean, &amp;amp;nbsp;Arithmetic Average.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>قياس فعالية القدرة الإدارية للمديرين التنفيذيين على العلاقة بين مستوى التحفظ المحاسبي وخطر الانهيار المستقبلي لأسعار الأسهم خلال جائحة COVID-19: دليل تطبيقي من البورصة المصرية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_291886.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;هدف البحث: قياس فعالية القدرة الإدارية للمديرين التنفيذيين على العلاقة بين مستوى التحفظ المحاسبي وخطر الانهيار المستقبلي لأسعار الأسهم خلال جائحة COVID-19، وذلك بالتطبيق على الشركات المساهمة غير المالية المدرجة في بورصة الأوراق المالية المصرية.التصميم والمنهجية: اعتمدت الدراسة على مدخل تحليل المحتوي فى فحص التقارير المالية للشركات المسجلة بالبورصة المصرية خلال فترة ما قبل جائحة COVID-19 (عام 2018 حتى عام 2019) والفترة خلال جائحة COVID-19 (عام 2020 حتى عام 2021)، بإجمالي مشاهدات ( 276) مشاهدة، وذلك لأغراض بناء (5) نماذج كمية لإختبار فروض الدراسة، وقد اعتمدت الدراسة الحالية على تحليل الانحدار الخطى متعدد المتغيرات باستخدام نموذج الانحدار ذات التأثير الثابت كأحد نماذج الانحدار الطولية لأسلوب Panal Data، من خلال برنامج (E-Views) الإصدار (12)، وبرنامج (SPSS) الإصدار (27).النتائج والتوصيات: توصلت الدراسة إلى عدة نتائج والتي من أهمها، توافرت أدلة إحصائية على وجود علاقة ارتباط موجبة ذات تأثير معنوى بين فعالية القدرة الإدارية للمديرين التنفيذيين ومستوى التحفظ المحاسبى بالتقارير المالية خلال جائحة .COVID-19 كما، توافرت أدلة إحصائية على وجود علاقة ارتباط سالبة ذات تأثير معنوي لمستوى التحفظ المحاسبى بالتقارير المالية على خطر الانهيار المستقبلي لأسعار الأسهم خلال جائحة .COVID-19 كذلك قدمت الدراسة دليلًا إحصائيًا على العلاقة التأثيرية السالبة بين مستوى التحفظ المحاسبى وخطر الانهيار المستقبلى لأسعار الأسهم خلال جائحة COVID-19، وقد ظهرت العلاقة بشكل أكثر تفسيراً بعد أضافة تأثير القدرة الإدارية للمديرين التنفيذيين كمتغير مُعدل لهذه لعلاقة، واستناداً للنتائج السابقة يوصى الباحث بتوجيه الفكر المحاسبي لأجراء مزيد من البحوث التى يمكن أن تقدم تفسيراً إضافياً عن العواقب الاقتصادية (الإيجابية والسلبية) للقدرة الإدارية للمديرين التنفيذيين على القيمة الاقتصادية المضافة للقطاع المصرفي المصري، وللقطاعات الصناعية التي تضررت خلال جائحة COVID-19.الأصالة والإضافة: تُعد هذه الدراسة بمثابة إضافة علمية حيث تُعد الأولى من نوعها في أدبيات الفكر المحاسبي والتمويلي، من خلال تقديمها لأدلة تفسيرية وقرائن عملية من الشركات المسجلة بالبورصة المصرية، فيما يتعلق بالمتغيرات البحثية للدراسة الحالية خلال جائحة COVID-19.&amp;amp;nbsp;Research objective: The Research aims to Measure the Effectiveness of the&amp;amp;nbsp;CEO's&amp;amp;nbsp;Managerial Ability&amp;amp;nbsp;on the Relationship between the level of&amp;amp;nbsp;Accounting Conservatism&amp;amp;nbsp;and the Future&amp;amp;nbsp;Stock Price Crash&amp;amp;nbsp;Risk&amp;amp;nbsp;during the COVID-19 pandemic. This is Applied to non-Financial listed Companies on the&amp;amp;nbsp;Egyptian Stock Exchange.Design and Methodology: The Study used&amp;amp;nbsp;Content Analysis&amp;amp;nbsp;to Examine the&amp;amp;nbsp;Financial Reports&amp;amp;nbsp;of Companies on the Egyptian Stock Exchange during the pre-COVID-19 period (2018-2019) and during the COVID-19 pandemic (2020-2021), with a total of 276 Observations. The Study built five Quantitative Models to test the Hypotheses, Using&amp;amp;nbsp;Multiple linear Regression Analysis,&amp;amp;nbsp;and the fixed-effects Regression Model&amp;amp;nbsp;as one of the&amp;amp;nbsp;longitudinal Regression Models&amp;amp;nbsp;for the&amp;amp;nbsp;Panal Data Method. The study used the E-Views (12) and&amp;amp;nbsp;SPSS (27)&amp;amp;nbsp;software programs.Results and Recommendations: The study found a Positive Correlation between the Effectiveness of CEO's&amp;amp;nbsp;Managerial Ability and Accounting Conservatism in Financial reports during the COVID-19 pandemic. Additionally, the Study found a significant&amp;amp;nbsp;negative Correlation&amp;amp;nbsp;between Accounting Conservatism in Financial Reports and the Future&amp;amp;nbsp;Stock Price Crash&amp;amp;nbsp;Risk during the COVID-19 pandemic. Furthermore, the study revealed the negative impact of accounting conservatism on the Future&amp;amp;nbsp;Stock Price Crash&amp;amp;nbsp;Risk during the COVID-19 pandemic, which became clearer after adding the effect of CEO's&amp;amp;nbsp;managerial Ability as a&amp;amp;nbsp;moderating variable. Based on these findings, the research recommends conducting further studies to provide additional explanations about the&amp;amp;nbsp;economic consequences&amp;amp;nbsp;of CEO's&amp;amp;nbsp;managerial Ability on the&amp;amp;nbsp;added economic value&amp;amp;nbsp;of the&amp;amp;nbsp;Egyptian banking sector&amp;amp;nbsp;and the industrial sectors that were affected during the COVID-19 pandemic.Originality&amp;amp;nbsp;and Contribution: This Study is the first of its kind in the literature of Accounting and Finance, Providing&amp;amp;nbsp;Interpretive evidence&amp;amp;nbsp;and practical indicators from companies listed on the&amp;amp;nbsp;Egyptian stock exchange, related to the research variables of the current study during the COVID-19 pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Cross-Border Listing Firms Manage Earnings? Evidence from Egyptian Stock Exchange</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285171.html</link>
      <description>Purpose &amp;amp;ndash; The purpose of this study is to examine whether cross-listing Egyptian firms in international stock exchanges are associated with improving the quality of reported earnings &amp;amp;nbsp;Design/Method &amp;amp;ndash; Depending on multivariate regression analysis, this study examined the impact of international cross-listing on the earnings management practices of Egyptian firms. &amp;amp;nbsp;Findings &amp;amp;ndash; Using earnings management practices as an inverse proxy for quality of financial reporting, this study found that cross-listed Egyptian firms tend to report larger value of discretionary accruals compared with non-cross-listed Egyptian firms after controlling for several firm-level characteristics that could influence managers&amp;amp;rsquo; incentives to manipulate earnings.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>اثر انشطة المسئولية الاجتماعية على التجنب الضريبي وانعكاسها على قيمة الشركات المدرجة بالمؤشر المصرى EGX100</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285172.html</link>
      <description>استهدف هذا البحث دراسة واختبار اثر انشطة المسئولية الاجتماعية على التجنب الضريبي ومدى انعكاس ذلك على قيمة المنشأة ، ولتحقيق هدف البحث تم تحليل الدراسات السابقة لاشتقاق الفروض ، ثم اجراء دراسة تطبيقية على 61 شركة مقيدة بالمؤشر المسئولية الاجتماعية EGX 100 خــــــلال الـفـتــــرة ربع السنوية مــن عــــــــام 2015 إلى 2020 وتم استخدام أسلوب البيانات الطولية Panel Data (longitudinal data) الذي يجمع بين كل من أسلوب البيانات القطاعية Cross Sectional Data&amp;amp;nbsp; وأسلوب السلاسل الزمنية Time Series Data، وكانت نتائج البحث كالاتى : 1) وجود علاقة ارتباط ذات دلالة إحصائية بين قيمة الشركة وكل من المسئولية الاجتماعية&amp;amp;nbsp; وحجم الشركة&amp;amp;nbsp; ومعدل العائد على الأصول&amp;amp;nbsp; والرافعة المالية&amp;amp;nbsp; وكثافة رأس المال &amp;amp;nbsp;، 2) لا توجد علاقة ارتباط ذات دلالة إحصائية بين المسئولية الاجتماعية &amp;amp;nbsp;والتجنب الضريبي&amp;amp;nbsp; ، 3) لا يوجد تأثير ذو دلالة إحصائية للتجنب الضريبي&amp;amp;nbsp; على قيمة الشركةThe research aimed to study and test the effect of corporate Social Responsibility activities on Tax Avoidance and its reflection on Firm value, to achieve the goal of the research, previous accounting studies were analyzed to derive research hypotheses, then an applied study was conducted on 61 companies registered in the value of companies listed in EGX 100 during the quarterly period from 2015 to 2020 . the Panel Data (longitudinal data) method was used , which combines the Cross Sectional Data and Time Series Data method , and the research results were as follows ; 1) there is a statistically significant correlation between the Firm value , corporate Social Responsibility, Firm size , rate of return on assets , leverage , and capital density.2) There is no statistically significant correlation between corporate Social Responsibility and Tax Avoidance 3) There is no statistically significant correlation between Tax Avoidance and Firm value</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور ادارة الأداء لزيادة قيمة المنشأة في ظل الفجوة الرقمية " دراسة تحليلية "</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285176.html</link>
      <description>تهدف هذه الدراسة الى إيضاح كيفية استطاعة إدارة الأداء زيادة قيمة المنشأة في ظل الفجوة الرقمية ، يشهد العالم اليوم تغيرات متلاحقة في تكنولوجيا المعلومات المحاسبية والتوسع في استخدام الشبكة الدولية، ونتيجة للتطورات التقنية وتكنولوجيا المعلومات والتغير التكنولوجيا الإنتاجية والمنافسة الشديدة بين المنشآت ولزيادة القدرة التنافسية والاستمرار والبفاء في عالم الاعمال ، ولاهمية البارزة لمنفعة وجدوى تكنولوجيا المعلومات التي تساعد في اتخاذ القرارات وتحديثها لتتلائم مع التطورات التكنولوجيا الحديثة والمتسارعة في بيئة التصنية المتطورة ، ولكن الفجوة الرقمية تعنى تباعد في منفعة وجدوى المعلومات التي تساعد إدارة الأداء في تطوير الأداء بهدف زيادة قيمة للمنشأةفى بيئة التصنيع .وقد قام الباحث بعمل دراسة ميدانية على عينة من المنشآت الصناعية مستخدما قائمة استقصاء اعدت لهذا الغرض وقد توصلنا إلى مجموعة من النتائج تجيب على فرضياتنا المتعلقة بموضوع.The study aims to illustrate how can the performance management apluse the firm value in the&amp;amp;nbsp; digital gap ,The world is witnessing today successive changes in accounting information technology, and expand the use of the International network for Information , Due to the great techvical development in the field of information technological and productive changes and intense competive changes and intense competition amange insititutes to ensure their survivol in the highiy competitive basiness world ,&amp;amp;nbsp; Due to the importance of the prominent role for the benefit of, value, and usefulness of the information technology to the helping in dicicion and upgrade tham to be adaptive to the modern accelerating technological development in the highly develape , The digital gap mean spacing in the benefit volue&amp;amp;nbsp;, and usefulness of the information to help the develapement aims aplus performance management the firm volue in manufacturing&amp;amp;nbsp; environment.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;Where the researcher selected field study and the to working the research from the manfactore , using questionnaires in this , We have reached a set of results that answer our assumptions regarding the topic .&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of Bitcoin as hedge, safe haven or diversifier for USA stock markets: Evidence from the DCC-GARCH approach</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285181.html</link>
      <description>The aim of this paper is to examine the hedging, safe haven and diversification abilities of Bitcoin in the stock, energy and currency markets. To do so, we collected daily data from 03 January 2011 to 18 October 2019. The results suggest that Bitcoin is considered an effective diversification tool for the stock and energy markets. However, it is a strong hedge for the currency market. In addition, they reported that Bitcoin represents a safe haven for the stock and energy markets. American investors are advised not to include Bitcoin in their portfolios massively as a safe haven, because this leads to increased volatility.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Moderating Influence of Ownership Structure on the Association between Financial Reporting Quality and Investment Efficiency: Evidence from Egypt</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285182.html</link>
      <description>The key purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of Financial Reporting Quality (FRQ) on Investment Efficiency (IE) in Egypt. In addition, this research studies the moderating effect of various structures of ownership (concentration and managerial ownership) on the association between FRQ and IE. The structure of ownership is an essential internal corporate governance mechanism that could solve agency issues and reduce information asymmetry Chen (2013) and Fama and Jensen (1983). This study used a sample of 53 companies that were registered on the Egyptian stock exchange )EGX( market between 2015 and 2018. According to the findings, FRQ and IE have a substantial positive association. Second, organizations with significant managerial ownership show a stronger correlation between FRQ and IE. Finally, the link between FRQ and IE is not being moderated by concentrated ownership. The study's findings are consistent with the idea that managerial ownership could decrease agency problems and information asymmetry. Therefore, providing managers with stock ownership as compensation will be quite advantageous.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تحليل العلاقة بين دورة حياة الشركة والقابلية للمقارنة للقوائم المالية في ظل التأثير المعدل لعدم تماثل المعلومات: دراسة تطبيقية على الشركات المساهمة غير المالية المقيدة بالبورصة المصرية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285184.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث إلى تحليل العلاقة بين مراحل دورة حياة الشركة (مقاسة بنمط التدفقات النقدية للشركة) على القابلية للمقارنة للقوائم المالية للشركات المساهمة غير المالية المقيدة بالبورصة المصرية وتأثير عدم تماثل المعلومات على تلك العلاقة. ومن خلال تحليل الدراسات السابقة تم اشتقاق فرضين رئيسين وتم استخدام اسلوب الانحدار البسيط والمتعدد لاختبار فرضى الدراسة، وبالاعتماد على البرنامج الإحصائي EViews 10، وبالتطبيق على بيانات 60 شركة من الشركات المساهمة غير المالية المقيدة ببورصة الأوراق المالية المصرية تنتمي إلى ثماني قطاعات مختلف، وذلك خلال الفترة من عام 2016 إلى عام 2019. وتوصلت الدراسة إلى القابلية للمقارنة للقوائم المالية للشركات المساهمة غير المالية المصرية تزداد في مرحلة النضوج مقارنة بالشركات الأخرى بصفة عامة وخاصة عند زيادة مستوي عدم تماثل المعلومات، لأن زيادة عدم تماثل المعلومات يوفر حوافز للمديرين للإفصاح عن قوائم مالية قابلة للمقارنة لتحسين جودة بيئة المعلومات، كما توصلت الدراسة إلى أن القابلية للمقارنة للقوائم المالية للشركات المساهمة غير المالية المصرية تزداد في مرحلة النمو عند زيادة مستوي عدم تماثل المعلومات فقط، وذلك نتيجة لأن زيادة عدم تماثل المعلومات يوفر حوافز للمديرين لزيادة مستويات الإفصاح لتوفير احتياجاتهم التمويلية مما يخفض من مستوي عدم تماثل المعلومات ويزيد من القابلية للمقارنة للقوائم المالية، وأخيرًا، توصلت الدراسة إلى أن القابلية للمقارنة للقوائم المالية للشركات المساهمة غير المالية المصرية تنخفض في مرحلة التقديم والتذبذب والتدهور.The research aims to analyze the relationship between the stages of firm life cycle (measured by the company's cash flow pattern) on the financial statement comparability of non-financial joint stock firms listed on the Egyptian Stock Exchange and the impact of information asymmetry on that relationship. Through the literature review, two main hypotheses were derived, we used Panel Regression to test the study hypotheses by relying on the EViews 10 statistical program, and by using data from 60 non-financial firms listed on the Egyptian stock exchange belonging to eight different sectors, during the period from 2016 to 2019.The study concluded that financial statement comparability of the non-financial firms listed on the Egyptian stock exchange increases in the maturity stage compared to other firms in general and especially when the level of information asymmetry is increased, because the increase in information asymmetry provides incentives for managers to disclose comparable financial statements to improve the quality of the information environment. The study also found that the financial statement comparability increases in the growth stage when the level of information asymmetry increases only, as a result of the increase in information asymmetry provides incentives for managers to increase disclosure levels to obtain their financing needs, which reduces the level of information asymmetry uniformity of information and increases the financial statement comparability. Finally, the study found that the financial statement comparability decreases in the introduction, shakeout and decline stages.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>توظيف الحوكمة الرقمية في ظل بيئة البيانات الكبيرة لدعم المحاسبة عن التنمية المستدامة (دراسة تطبيقية)</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285186.html</link>
      <description>استهدفت الدراسة تقديم رؤية مستقبلية حول قبول تبنى أعمال وممارسات المراجعة السحابية في بيئة الأعمال المصرية وعلاقة ذلك بخدمات المحاسبة السحابية بالإستناد إلى توظيف نموذج قبول التكنولوجيا الذي يستند إلى عاملين رئيسيين في مهنة المراجعة هما: الفائدة المدركة، وسهولة الاستخدام المتوقعة. ولتحقيق ذلك تم صياغة الجوانب الفكرية لخدمات المحاسبة السحابية ومدى حاجة المنظمات لأعمال وممارسات المراجعة السحابية. بالإضافة إلى نموذج قبول التكنولوجيا وتوظيفه في اختبار العلاقة التأثيرية بينهما. وأخيراً أجريت دراسة تطبيقية تم من خلالها اختبار فروض البحث.&amp;amp;nbsp;أظهرت نتائج التحليل الإحصائي أن كلا من خدمات المحاسبة السحابية، والفائدة المدركة من استخدام المراجعة السحابية، والسهولة المتوقعة من استخدام المحاسبة السحابية لها تأثيراً معنوياً على توجه المنظمات نحو قبول التبني المستقبلي لأعمال وممارسات المراجعة السحابية. ولقد أشارت المؤشرات الإحصائية إلى أن العوامل المرتبطة بالسهولة المتوقعة من استخدام المراجعة السحابية من أكثر العوامل تأثيراً في توجه المنظمات المصرية نحو التبني المستقبلي لأعمال وممارسات المراجعة السحابيةوقد أوصت الدراسة بتوجيه انتباه إدارة الشركات بأهمية تطبيق معايير وإرشادات المراجعة السحابية الدولية وتحديثاتها وتنمية المهارات التكنولوجية لمراجعي الحسابات، من أجل احتضان واستخدام تكنولوجيا الحوسبة السحابية والعمل على الترويج لها وخاصة في مجال الخدمات المحاسبية؛ لما سيكون للمراجعة السحابية من أهمية بالغة في التطوير المتجدد لمهنة المحاسبة والمراجعة في المستقبل القريب.The study aimed to provide a future vision on the acceptance of the adoption of cloud auditing practices in the Egyptian business environment and its relationship to cloud accounting services based on employing a technology acceptance model that is based on two main factors in the auditing profession: Perceived Usefulness and Perceived Ease of Use. To achieve this, the intellectual aspects of cloud accounting services and the extent to which organizations need cloud auditing work and practices have been formulated. In addition, to the model of accepting technology and employing it in testing the impact of relationship between them. Finally, the hypotheses of the research were tested through an applied study.The results of the statistical analysis showed that cloud accounting services, the perceived benefit of using cloud auditing, and the expected ease of using cloud accounting have a significant impact on the orientation of organizations towards accepting future adoption of cloud auditing work and practices.&amp;amp;nbsp; Statistical indicators have indicated that the factors associated with the expected ease of using cloud review are among the most influential factors in the orientation of Egyptian organizations toward the future adoption of cloud audit work and practices.The study recommended directing the attention of corporate management to the importance of applying international cloud auditing standards and guidelines and their updates and developing the technical skills of auditors, to embrace and use cloud computing technology and work to promote it, especially in the field of accounting services, as cloud auditing will be of great importance in the development of the accounting and auditing profession shortly.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>الدور المقترح لمراجع الحسابات في اضفاء الثقة على تقرير إدارة مخاطرالأمن السيبراني وأثره في دلالة القوائم المالية دراسة تجريبية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285187.html</link>
      <description>كأشارات علي ضعف الرقابة الداخلية يمكن ان تمثل حوادث الامن السيبراني عوامل خطر كبيرة لجودة التقارير المالية و نظرا لزيادة عدد حوادث الامن السيبراني وانتشارها لتبني&amp;amp;nbsp; كثيرا من الشركات التحول الرقمي ، ونظرا لتغير طبيعة النشاط في الشركات و خاصة العاملة في قطاع تكنولوجيا المعلومات ،جاء البحث ليناقش الدور المقترح لمراجع الحسابات في اضفاء الثقة علي تقرير ادارة مخاطر الامن السيبراني حتي يستطيع المراجع مواكبة التغير السريع في بيئة الاعمال.و تتمثل مشكلة البحث في التحديات التي تواجة المراجع متمثلة في حوادث الامن السيبراني ومخاطرها الكبيرة علي البرامج و التطبيقات المالية و صحة التقارير المالية و ما يتبعها من اضرار لاحقة لعملية اختراق البيانات وكيفية مواجهتها بل وعلي الاكثر من ذلك توقع هذة الهجمات و محاولة التخلص منها.جاء البحث بهدف اظهار دور المراجع في اضفاء الثقة علي تقرير ادارة مخاطر الامن السيبراني&amp;amp;nbsp; ،واثره علي دلالة القوائم المالية ولتحقيق الهدف الرئيسي للبحث قامت الباحثة باستخدم الدراسة التجريبية و هي مناسبة تماما لهذا النوع من البحوث فهي تدرس&amp;amp;nbsp; العلاقة السببية بين متغيرات مستقلة وتابعة ،وبصفه خاصة تأثير الدور المقترح لمراجع الحسابات علي اضفاء الثقة علي تقرير ادارة مخاطر الامن السيبراني ،فالتجارب تعتبر منهجا قويا يمكن للباحثين الاستدلال عن طريقه علي العلاقات السببية ،كما تمكن التجارب من توضيح التأثيرات الفعلية لانواع مختلفة من المعلومات علي عملية اتخاذ القرارات ،و بما يسمح بتطوير يفيد في تطوير المعرفة في موضوع الدراسة الحالية.&amp;amp;nbsp;تم اجراء الدراسة التجريبية علي مجتمع واحد و هو مجتمع مراجعي الحسابات العاملين في مكاتب المحاسبة و المراجعة بالمجتمع المصري خلال العام 2021 و 2022.و تكونت العينة من 400 مراجع حسابات طبقت عليهم الاستبانة ،و لم يتم استبعاد اي من الردود نظرا لاستخدام النشر الالكتروني للاستبيان عبر موقع Research Gate&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;وهو يحتوي علي مجموعة كبيرة من الفئة المستهدفة للدراسة.،كما استخدمت الدراسة اربعة متغيرات معدلة يمكن تعريف المتغيرات المعدلة بأنها المتغيرات التي تؤثر في اتجاة او قوة العلاقة بين المتغيرات المستقلة والتابعة ، كما تختلف المتغيرات المعدلة عن المتغيرات الرقابية حيث ثؤثر المتغيرات الرقابية علي المتغيرالتابع مباشرة.و خلصت الدراسة الي وجود تأثير معنوي لاهمية الافصاح عن تقرير ادارة مخاطر الامن السيبراني ,ووجود تأثيرمعنوي للدور المقترح لمراجع الحسابات&amp;amp;nbsp; و اثره علي القوائم المالية .As Signals of weak internal control, cybersecurity incidents can represent major risk factors for the quality of financial reports, and due to the increase in the number of cybersecurity incidents and their spread, many companies adopt digital transformation, and due to the change in the nature of activity in companies, especially those operating in the information technology sector, the idea of research came to discuss The proposed role of the auditor in giving confidence to the cybersecurity risk management report so that the auditor can keep pace with the rapid change in the business environment.The research problem is represented in the challenges that the auditors face, represented in cybersecurity incidents and their great risks to financial programs and applications, the validity of financial reports, and the subsequent damages to the data penetration process, how to confront them, and even more so to anticipate these attacks and try to get rid of them.The research came with the aim of showing the role of the references in giving confidence to the cyber security risk management report, and its impact on the significance of the financial statements. The proposed role of the auditor is to give confidence to the cybersecurity risk management report. Experiments are considered a powerful approach through which researchers can infer causal relationships. Experiments also enable clarification of the actual effects of different types of information on the decision-making process, allowing for useful development. Knowledge of the topic of the current study.The experimental study was conducted on one community, which is the community of auditors working in accounting and auditing offices in the Egyptian community during the years 2021 and 2022.The sample consisted of 400 auditors to whom the questionnaire was applied, and none of the responses were excluded due to the use of electronic publication of the questionnaire through the Research Gate website, which contains a large group of the target group for the study.The study also used four modified variables. The modified variables can be defined as the variables that affect the direction or strength of the relationship between the independent and dependent variables. The modified variables differ from the control variables, as the control variables affect the dependent variable directly.The study concluded that there is a significant impact of the importance of disclosing the cybersecurity risk management report, and that there is a significant impact of the proposed role of the auditor and its impact on the financial statements.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the Impact of Sustainability on Corporate Profitability: Evidence from Egypt</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285191.html</link>
      <description>The aim of this research is to investigate whether corporate sustainable performance (CSP) impacts corporate profitability. The study&amp;amp;rsquo;s sample includes the most active 100 listed firms in the Egyptian stock exchange (EGX) in terms of their trading value. Empirical analysis has been conducted to examine the impact of sustainability environmental, social, and governance (ESG) factors on corporate profitability using the regression model. In addition, the study seeks to determine whether highly ranked businesses outperform those with lower rankings in terms of sustainability. A parametric t-test was used. The study demonstrates a considerable positive association between sustainability and company profitability metrics, measured by Return on Assets (ROA), Return on Equity (ROE), and Return on Invested Capital (ROIC). Furthermore, empirical data indicate that businesses that adopt outstanding sustainable improvement strategies report increased profitability and lower levels of risk.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>إطار مقترح للمحاسبة عن الأصول الرأسمالية الحكومية في ظل المحاسبة على أساس الاستحقاق</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285193.html</link>
      <description>يهدف هذا البحث إلى تقديم مساهمة تتعلق بمشكلة الإفصاح عن الأصول الرأسمالية الحكومية في ظل تطبيق أساس الاستحقاق المحاسبي وفقاً لمبادئ الإدارة العامة الجديدة New Public Management (NPM)، وتضييق فجوة المعلومات بين كل من معدي القوائم المالية والمستخدمين من خلال اقتراح إطار متكامل للمحاسبة عن الأصول الرأسمالية الحكومية وفقاً لأساس الاستحقاق المحاسبي، بما يلبي حاجات المستخدمين من المعلومات المالية ويعمل على توليد معاني مشتركة (تفاهم) بين المعدين والمستخدمين حول المعلومات المفصح عنها. لأغراض تحقيق هذا الهدف، قام الباحث بدراسة وتحليل مساهمات جهات وضع المعايير الدولية والأمريكية والباحثين المرتبطة بشكل وثيق بالتقرير المحاسبي عن الأصول الرأسمالية الحكومية. وخلص البحث إلى اقتراح إطار محاسبي من منظور كلي للإفصاح عن هذه الأصول. يستند هذا الإطار على ستة معايير للاعتراف بالأصول الرأسمالية، مع تصنيف الأصول الرأسمالية التي تستوفي هذه المعايير إلى فئات رئيسية وفرعية تراعي طبيعتها وسماتها المميزة أو المتفردة، أما بالنسبة للأصول الرأسمالية التي لا تستوفي هذه المعايير فيتم معالجتها كأصول مقيدة، ويتم توفير معلومات عنها خارج القوائم المالية وفقاً للإطار المقترح.The purpose of this paper is to contribute to the debate related to the disclosure of governmental capital assets according to the accrual basis and New Public Management reforms, limit the information gap between both preparers and users of financial statements, meets the users&amp;amp;rsquo; needs of financial information, and generate common meanings (understanding) between producers and users about the disclosed information. To achieve these purposes, the researcher has studied and analyzed the contributions of international and American standards-setting bodies and researchers closely related to the accounting of governmental capital assets. The research proposed an accounting framework from a holistic perspective for the disclosure of these assets. This framework is based on six criteria for recognizing capital assets, then classifying the capital assets that meet these criteria into main and sub-categories according to their nature and distinctive or unique features. Capital assets that do not meet these criteria are treated as restricted assets, and information about them is provided outside the financial statements in accordance with the proposed framework.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر الإفصاح عن المعلومات المستقبلية على قيمة المنشأة: دراسة تطبيقية على سوق الأوراق المالية المصرية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285197.html</link>
      <description>هدف البحث إلى: تحليل الإفصاح عن المعلومات المستقبلية في القوائم والتقارير المالية السنوية للشركات المدرجة في البورصة المصرية، واختبار أثر هذا الإفصاح على قيمة المنشأة.التصميم والمنهجية: اعتمدت البحث على مدخل تحليل المحتوى في فحص القوائم والتقارير المالية، وتقارير مجلس الإدارة السنوية لعينة قوامها 50 شركة من الشركات المقيدة في البورصة المصرية، حيث تغطى البيانات فترة زمنية مدتها 5 سنوات من عام 2016 حتى عام 2020، وإجراء دراسة تطبيقية لاختبار فرض البحث، ويستند هذا البحث في تحليل بياناتها على برنامج EViews &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;وتم استخدام بيانات سلاسل زمنية وأسلوب تحليل الإطارية في تحليل النتائج.النتائج والتوصيات: تشير نتائج هذا البحث إلى وجود أثر ذو دلالة إحصائية للإفصاح عن المعلومات المستقبلية على قيمة المنشأة في البورصة المصرية، وأظهرت نتائج البحث إلى أن الإفصاح عن المعلومات المستقبلية تساعد في تحسين مراقبة منشآت الأعمال من قبل أصحاب المصالح وبخاصة المستثمرين وغيرهم. واستنادًا إلى ذلك يوصى البحث بضرورة قيام الشركات بالتوسع في مستوى الإفصاح وذلك من أجل تعزيز كفاءة السوق المالي المصري وجذب مزيد من فرص استثمارية جديدة، وبالإضافة إلى تطوير القوانين والمعايير الخاصة بالإفصاح المستقبلي مع إجراء مزيد البحوث العلمية في هذا المجال.The aim of the research is to: analyze the disclosure of future information in the annual financial statements and reports of companies listed on the Egyptian Stock Exchange, and test the impact of this disclosure on the value of the enterprise.Design and methodology: The study relied on the content analysis approach in examining the financial statements and reports, and the annual reports of the Board of Directors for a sample of 50 companies listed on the Egyptian Stock Exchange, where the data covers a period of time of 5 years from 2016 to 2020, and an applied study was conducted to test the hypothesis The study, and this study is based on the analysis of its data on the EViews program, and time series data and the framework analysis method were used to analyze the results.The aim of the research is to: analyze the disclosure of future information in the annual financial statements and reports of companies listed on the Egyptian Stock Exchange, and test the impact of this disclosure on the value of the enterprise.Findings and Recommendations: The results of this research indicate that there is a statistically significant impact of the disclosure of future information on the value of the facility in the Egyptian Stock Exchange. Based on that, the study recommended that companies should expand the level of disclosure in order to enhance the efficiency of the Egyptian financial market and attract more new investment opportunities, in addition to developing laws and standards for future disclosure with further scientific research in this field.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر تكاليف الجودة على المؤشرات المالية التشغيلية وانعكاسها على التمويل الموجه للشركات المُدرجة ببورصة النيل : مع دراسة تطبيقية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285205.html</link>
      <description>هدفت الدراسة: إلى بيان أثر تكاليف الجودة على المؤشرات المالية التشغيلية وبيان انعكاس هذا الأثر على التمويل الموجه للشركات الصناعية والخدمية ببورصة النيل.التصميم والمنهجية: اعتمدت الدراسة على مدخل تحليل المحتوى من خلال فحص القوائم المالية للشركات والتي تمثلت في عدد 8 شركات بإجمالي 14 مشاهدة بغرض تجميع بيانات المتغير الوسيط والتابع، كما تم الاعتماد على الاستبيان الإلكتروني والمقابلات الشخصية لعدد من المدراء الماليين ومديري علاقات المستثمرين للشركات بهدف تجميع بيانات المتغير المستقل، وتم بناء أربع نماذج رئيسية لاختبار فروض الدراسة من خلال الاستعانة بالبرنامج الإحصائي (Spss.V,26) وتم استخدام كلاً من تحليل الانحدار المتعدد والبسيط كما تم الاستعانة بالتحليل الإحصائي (Sobel-Test)&amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;النتائج والتوصيات: توصلت نتائج الدراسة التطبيقية إلى وجود أثر ذو دلالة إحصائية لتكاليف الجودة على حجم التمويل الموجه للشركات الصناعية والخدمية المُدرجة ببورصة النيل بوساطة المؤشرات المالية التشغيلية المتمثلة في التدفق النقدي التشغيلي، ومؤشر كفاية التدفقات النقدية التشغيلية، ومؤشر معدل نمو التدفق التشغيلي.توصي الباحثة: ضرورة أن تتضمن قواعد الإفصاح للشركات المُقيدة بأسواق الأوراق المالية قيد مُلزم للإفصاح عن تكاليف الجودة كبند مستقل ضمن بنود تكاليف العمليات.Study objective: measuring the impact of quality costs on the operational financial indicators and show the reflection of this impact on the volume of funding directed to industrial and service companies listed on the Nile Stock Exchange.Design and methodology: the study was based on the method of content analysis of the financial statements published on the official website of the Nile Stock Exchange to collect the study data, while the researcher relied on both the questionnaire and personal interviews to collect the data of the independent variable, the study hypotheses were tested using multiple and simple regression analysis &amp;amp;nbsp;using the statistical program (Spss.V,26) and a significant test Mediation with the (Sobel Test).&amp;amp;nbsp;The results of the applied study concluded and showed that there is a statistically significant effect of quality costs on the volume of financing directed to industrial and service companies listed on the Nile Stock Exchange through the operational financial indicators.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>استخدام مدخليّ التكلفة على أساس الأنشطة الموجهة بالوقت وتحليل القيمة لتعزيز قيمة خدمات الرعاية الصحية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285210.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; استهدف البحث بيان أثر تكامل مدخليّ التكلفة على أساس الأنشطة الموجهة بالوقت Time-driven activity-based costing (TDABC) وتحليل القيمة Value Analysis (VA) على تخفيض تكاليف تقديم الخدمات بمنشآت الرعاية الصحية دون التأثير على جودتها المدركة من جانب المنتفعين (المرضى)، وفي سبيل ذلك تم التطرق لطبيعة الخدمات المقدمة بمنشآت الرعاية الصحية من منظور محاسبي، وكذلك سمات جودة الخدمات الصحية المفترض أن تؤدى بها. ولتوضيح كيفية تطوير نظام محاسبة التكاليف المطبق بمنشآت الرعاية الصحية أجرى الباحث تحليلاً فكرياً لمدخليّ TDABC وVA انتهاءً بتوضيح كيفية إحداث تكامل بينهما يُسهم في الارتقاء بدقة القياس التكاليفي لخدمات الرعاية الصحية، وانعكاس ذلك على تعزيز قيمة وظائف هذه الخدمات من منظور المنتفعين وفي ضوء معايير الأداء التي يجب أن تُؤدى بها. وتوصل الباحث إلى أن استخدام مدخليّ TDABC وVA في إطارٍ تكامليّ من شأنه تعزيز قيمة خدمات الرعاية الصحية؛ حيث موارد المنشأة يتم استغلالها بالقدر المحقق للجودة المدركة من قبل المنتفعين بهذه الخدمات.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; ويوصي الباحث بأهمية النظر بشكلٍ دوري ودائم إلى ركائز جودة أداء الخدمة الصحية جنباً إلى جنب مع التكاليف المتكبدة في تحقيقها وذلك في ضوء استخدام مدخليّ TDABC وVA؛ لضمان استدامة أعمالها على نحوٍ كفؤ وفعّال.Objective of the research is to demonstrate the effect of integrating Time-driven Activity-based Costing (TDABC) and Value Analysis (VA) approaches on reducing the costs of providing services in health care facilities without affecting their perceived quality by beneficiaries (patients). For this purpose, the nature of the services provided in healthcare facilities was addressed from an accounting perspective, as well as the quality characteristics of the healthcare services that are supposed to be provided. In order to clarify how to develop the cost accounting system applied in healthcare facilities, the researcher conducted an intellectual analysis of the two approaches; TDABC and VA, ending with clarifying how the integration between them contributes improving the accuracy of cost measurement of &amp;amp;nbsp;healthcare services, and its reflection on enhancing the value of the functions of these services from the perspective of the beneficiaries and in the light of the performance standards that must be performed. The researcher concluded that using the TDABC and VA approaches in an integrative framework would enhance the value of healthcare services functions; where the resources of the facility are exploited to the extent of achieving the quality perceived by the beneficiaries of these services. The researcher recommends the importance of looking periodically and permanently at the pillars of the quality of healthcare services performance along with the costs incurred in achieving it, in light of using the TDABC and VA approaches; to ensure the sustainability of its business in an efficient and effective manner.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دراسة تحليلية للعلاقة بين القدرة الإدارية وممارسات تمهيد الدخل وآثارها على جودة المحتوى المعلوماتي للتقارير المالية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285211.html</link>
      <description>تستهدف هذه الدراسة توضيح طبيعة العلاقة بين درجة القدرة الإدارية وممارسات تمهيد الدخل وآثارها على جودة المحتوى المعلوماتي للتقارير المالية، وذلك في إطار نظري، يشمل تحديد الإطار المفاهيمي لمتغيرات الدراسة، ثم عرض وتحليل الدراسات السابقة ذات الصلة بهذه العلاقة. خلُص الباحث من تحليل تلك الدراسات، إلى وجود اهتمام من قبل الدراسات السابقة لاختبار العلاقة بين درجة القدرة الإدارية وممارسات تمهيد الدخل، ومدى تأثيرها على جودة المحتوى المعلوماتي للتقارير المالية في الأسواق المالية بصفة عامة، والأسواق الناشئة (ومنها السوق المصري) بصفة خاصة. وفيما يتعلق بإتجاه وتأثير العلاقة بين درجة القدرة الإدارية والبيئة المعلوماتية ومستوى الإفصاح في التقارير المالية للشركات، توصل الباحث إلى وجود علاقة موجبة جوهرية بينهما. أما فيما يتعلق بإتجاه وتأثير العلاقة بين درجة القدرة الإدارية، وبين ممارسات تمهيد الدخل، وآثارها على جودة المحتوى المعلوماتي للتقارير المالية، اتضح للباحث أن نتائج الدراسات السابقة قد توصلت إلى وجود علاقة ارتباط موجبة معنوية لدرجة القدرة الإدارية على مستوى أنشطة وممارسات تمهيد الدخل، ولكن تباينت آثارها على جودة المحتوى المعلوماتي للتقارير المالية، حيث أظهر تحليلها وجود تعارض واضح في النتائج. لذا، يرى الباحث أنه من الملائم اختبار هذه العلاقة بالتطبيق العملي على سوق الأوراق المالية المصرية.This study aims to review literature concerning the relationship between degree of managerial ability and income smoothing practices and its effect on quality of the informational content of financial reports, in a theoretical framework, including identifying the conceptual framework of the study variables, and then presenting and analyzing previous studies. The researcher concluded that, there is interest from previous studies to test the relationship between managerial ability and income smoothing practices, and its effect on quality of the informational content of financial reports in financial markets in general, and emerging markets (including the Egyptian market) in particular. With regard to the direction and impact of the relationship between the degree of managerial ability and Information environment and disclosure level in corporate financial reports, the researcher concluded that there is a positive and significant relationship between them. As for the direction and impact of the relationship between the degree of managerial ability, income smoothing practices, and its effect on quality of the informational content of financial reports, It became clear to the researcher that the results of literature review have found a significant positive correlation with the degree of of managerial ability at the level of income smoothing activities and practices, However, their effects on the quality of the informational content of financial reports varied, Where her analysis showed a clear conflict in the results. Therefore, the researcher believes that it would be appropriate to test this relationship with practical application on the Egyptian stock market.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>أثر تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل على دور المراجع الخارجي- دراسة ميدانية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285321.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; تناولت الدراسة أثر استخدام تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل (Blockchain) على دور المراجع الخارجي. حيث تم توضيح ذلك من خلال عرض للفرص والتحديات التى تواجه المراجع الخارجي فى ظل تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل، بالإضافة إلى عرض للوظائف المستحدثة للمراجع الخارجي فى ظل تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل، وقد تم الاعتماد على أسلوب العينة العشوائية الطبقية فى اختيار عينة الدراسة والمكونة من 167 مفردة، وقد شملت ثلاث فئات هم ( أعضاء هيئة التدريس &amp;amp;ndash; مراجعو الحسابات &amp;amp;ndash; العاملون بشركات لديها نظام قائم على تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل). وقد أثبتت الدراسة الميدانية أن استخدام تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل سوف يؤدى إلى تطوير دور المراجع الخارجى وذلك عن طريق إضافة وظائف مستحدثة للمراجع منها (مراجعة العقود الذكية، مراجعة الأصول الرقمية، المراجع كعامل يحد من اتفاق الأغلبية، وظيفة منح حق الوصول، وظيفة التحكيم بين المشاركين بالسلسلة). وتوصلت الدراسة إلى قبول فروض الدراسة وهى؛ أن هناك علاقة إيجابية بين تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل وبين الفرص والتحديات التى تواجه المراجع الخارجي فى ظل تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل، وأن هناك علاقة إيجابية بين تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل وبين تطور وظائف المراجع الخارجي.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study examined the impact of using blockchain technology on the role of the external auditor, which was clarified through a presentation of the opportunities and challenges facing the external auditor when using the block chain technology, in addition to a presentation of the functions created for the external auditor using the block chain technology. The stratified random sampling method was used to select the study sample, which consisted of (167) individuals. It included three categories (faculty members - auditors - employees of companies that have a system based on blockchain technology). The empirical study has proven that the use of block chain technology will lead to the development of the role of the external auditor by adding new functions for the auditor, including (reviewing smart contracts, reviewing digital assets, auditors as a factor that limits majority agreement, the function of granting access, and the function of arbitration between participants in the chain). The study reached the acceptance of the study hypotheses, which are; That there is a positive relationship between the block chain technology and the opportunities and challenges facing the external auditor by using the block chain technology, and that there is a positive relationship between the block chain technology and the development of the functions of the external auditor.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>إطار مقترح للمراجعة فى ظل المخاطر الكامنة لتكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل دراسة ميدانية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285328.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; تناولت الدراسة مخاطر المراجعة الكامنة فى ظل تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل ووضع إطار مقترح &amp;amp;nbsp;يحدد دور المراجع الخارجي بناءً على المخاطر الكامنة لها . حيث تم توضيح ذلك من خلال عرض لأنواع المخاطر الكامنة فى ظل تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل والتى تضمنت على " مخاطر آلية حوكمة الشبكات وتوافق آراء المشاركين بالشبكة، مخاطر سرية البيانات، مخاطر ربط بروتوكولات سلسلة الكتل المختلفة، مخاطر إدارة المفاتيح الخاصة، مخاطر الاندماج، مخاطر&amp;amp;nbsp; القابلية للتوسع، مخاطر تكنولوجيا المعلومات، مخاطر العقود الذكية، مخاطر النمو التكنولوجى وتطوير الكود، مخاطر استمرارية الأعمال والتعافى من الكوارث"، وفى ضوء تحقيق الهدف من الدراسة، تقدم الدراسة إطارًا مقترحًا يعمل على تحديد دور المراجع فى ظل المخاطر الكامنة لتكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل، وقد تم الاعتماد على أسلوب العينة العشوائية الطبقية فى اختيار عينة الدراسة والمكونة من (167) مفردة، وقد شملت ثلاث فئات هم ( أعضاء هيئة التدريس &amp;amp;ndash; مراجعو الحسابات &amp;amp;ndash; العاملون بشركات لديها نظام قائم على تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل ) . وقد أثبتت الدراسة الميدانية أن المراجع الخارجى يواجه مخاطر مستحدثة فى ظل تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل، وتشتمل على( مخاطر متعلقة بآلية حوكمة الشبكات وتوافق آراء المشاركين بالشبكة، مخاطر متعلقة بسرية البيانات، مخاطر متعلقة بربط بروتوكولات سلسلة الكتل المختلفة، مخاطر متعلقة بإدارة المفاتيح الخاصة، مخاطر متعلقة بالاندماج، مخاطر متعلقة بقابلية التوسع، مخاطر متعلقة بتكنولوجيا المعلومات، مخاطر متعلقة بالعقود الذكية، مخاطر متعلقة بالنمو التكنولوجى وتطوير الكود، مخاطر متعلقة باستمرارية الأعمال والتعافى من الكوارث). وتوصلت الدراسة إلى قبول فروض الدراسة وهى؛ "أن هناك علاقة إيجابية بين تطور المراجعة والمخاطر الكامنة لتكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل" ، و"أن هناك علاقة إيجابية بين الإطار المقترح وتطور مراجعة تكنولوجيا سلسلة الكتل".&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study addressed the audit risks when using the blockchain technology and developed a proposed framework that defines the role of the external auditor based on the inherent risks of the blockchain technology. Where this was clarified through a presentation of the types of risks inherent in by using the block chain technology, which included "the risks of the network governance mechanism and the consensus of the network participants, the risks of data confidentiality, the risks of linking the different block chain protocols, the risks of managing private keys, the risks of merger, the risks of scalability Information technology risks, smart contract risks, technological growth risks and code development, business continuity risks and disaster recovery. Through achieving the objective of the study, the study presents a proposed framework that defines the role of the auditor using the inherent risks of blockchain technology. The stratified random sample method was relied upon to select the study sample, which consisted of 167 individuals, and it included three categories: (faculty members - auditors - employees of companies that have a system based on blockchain technology). The field study has proven that the external auditor faces new risks through using the blockchain technology, which include (risks related to the network governance mechanism and the consensus of network participants, risks related to data confidentiality, risks related to linking different block chain protocols, risks related to managing private keys, risks related to risks related to merger, scalability risks, information technology risks, smart contracts risks, technological growth risks and code development, business continuity risks and disaster recovery). The study reached the acceptance of the study hypotheses, which are; There is a positive relationship between the development of auditing and the inherent risks of blockchain technology, and that there is a positive relationship between the proposed framework and the development of auditing of block chain technology.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تاثير مصادر التمويل الخارجي على النمو الاقتصادي في مصر وبعض الدول النامية خلال الفترة (2000–2018)</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_281388.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث الى الاستفاده من تجارب الدول فى تعبئه الموارد المحليه والخارجيه من اجل تحقيق التنميه المستدامه مع اهميه توفير معايير ومؤشرات حول كفاءه تعبئه وانفاق هذه الموارد واقتراح السياسات والاطار المؤسسي المرتبط بتعبئه المدخرات والاسثتمارات المواءمه لهذا المناخ.وفي ضوء تناول كفاءه مصادر التمويل الخارجي وفقا للعديد من الدراسات , تشير النتائج الى ان اثار هذه التدفقات : اسثتمارات اجنبيه مباشره , تحويلات عوائد العماله المهاجره, والقروض المصرفيه محدوده بدلاله معدل النمو الاقتصادي, التشغيل, وتقليص حده الفقر. لذلك فانه من الاهميه دراسه تاثير السياسات الاقتصاديه بالاضافه للعوامل الاخري على كفاءه تاثير مصادر التمويل الاجنبي الخارجي على النمو الاقتصادي على جوده السياسات الاقتصاديه التى تستخدمها الحكومات , كذلك فان الكفاءه النسبيه لكل مصدر من مصادر التمويل الخارجي تعتمد على الاستبدال او التكامليه بين المصادر الثلاثه , ويظل الهدف الرئيسي للدراسه الحاليه هو البحث عن اى مصادر التمويل الخارجي الاكثر فعاليه فى تمويل التنميه, وماهي توليفه هذه المصادر الاكثر امثليه لدعم النمو الاقتصاديTHE study focused on discussing and analyzing the benefits and burdens attributed to the external resources of finance FDI, Loans and remittances,in order to measure its efficiency and effectiveness,In addition , the study measures quantatively the external resources impacts on economic growth.The findings from the study reveal that the external resources are not considered as a substitute for the self-financing has to be linked with development the production capabilities and increasing income in a way that exceeds debt service and amortization costs.The analysis show that the foreign investments in the Egyptian production sectors have not contributed singnificantly to technology transfer. Therefore, in terms of costs and benefits accounts, external debt is not an efficient option to substitute for domestic debt. The study highlights the importance of remittances as counter-economic cycles, although being unproductive.The empirical analysis reveals that there is a positive relationship between the foreign direct investment and economic growth .On the contrary, remittances, ODAS(net) and external debts have exerted negative impacts on economic growth.The implications resulting from the finding include some directives of policies to attract FDI, and development the infrastructure.Also, reorienting remittances towards the productive areas as well as rationalization of the external debt management are advised to maximize benefits and reduce costs on economic growth</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>دور الشباب في تحقيق التنمية المستدامة في مصر</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285144.html</link>
      <description>تهدف الدراسة لقياس دور الشباب المصري في تحقيق التنمية المستدامة في جمهورية مصر العربية من خلال البحث في العديد من الدراسات السابقة التي تمت في السبع سنوات الماضية 2015 وحتي 2022 ، ومن الناحية الاخري تم استخدلم نموذج&amp;amp;nbsp; OLS لايجاد العلاقة بين المتغيرات المتعددة للدراسة ، وانقسم البحث الي ثلاثة مباحث تناول المبحث الأول : مفهوم الشباب واهميتهم و تناول الثاني: مفهوم التنمية المستدامة و اهم مبادئها و تناول الثالث: قياس بدور الشباب في تحقيق التنمية المستدامة من خلال تطبيق نموذج قياسي يدمج مجموعة من المتغيرات الخاصة بقياس التنمية المستدامة ونسبة مشاركة القوي العاملة للشباب في قوة العمل في مصر، ومن خلال المناقشات الوصفية و الجزء القياسي توصلت الدراسة الي العديد من النتائج كان اهمها ان للشباب دور محوري في تحقيق التنمية المستدامة المستدام في مصر وان اغفال دور الشباب في التنمية له تبعات خطيرة علي مستوي المجتمع.&#13;
This study aims to measure the role of Egyptian youth in achieving sustainable development in Arab Republic of Egypt, furthermore the study focused on scientific literature review related to this topic, on the other hand we used OLS model to find the relationship between various variables the study divided into three sections, the first section focused on : the concept of youth and their importance, and the second focused on : the concepts of sustainable development, The third section focused on the&amp;amp;nbsp; Measuring the role of youth in achieving sustainable development through the application of an econometric model that integrates a set of variables for measuring sustainable development and the percentage of youth labor force participation in the labor force in Egypt. Finally, the study concluded many results, the most important of which was that youth have an active role in achieving sustainable development in Egypt</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Effect of Social Expenditure on Poverty Reduction and Growth in High- and Middle-Income Countries: A Dynamic Panel Analysis Applying the GMM Approach</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285151.html</link>
      <description>This study's primary objective is to evaluate the impact of social spending on economic development and poverty reduction for a sample of high- and middle-income nations from 2010 to 2018. To achieve this aim, the study applies the GMM approach to two models. First, the study investigate&amp;amp;nbsp;the impact of social spending on reducing poverty in high- and middle-income nations using Model A (the poverty model). Second, the study assesses the impact of social spending on economic growth in high- and middle-income nations using Model B (the growth model). The results of this analysis show that social spending, in both high- and middle-income nations, has beneficial effects on economic growth and negative effects on poverty. Additionally, the study finds that the biggest influences on economic growth, GDP, and poverty are expenditures on health, education, subsidies, and transfers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>الاقتصاد الرقمي وتعزيز تنافسية البنوك التجارية في مصر دراسة ميدانية</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285159.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; يهدف هذا البحث إلي التعرف علي أثر الاقتصاد الرقمي علي زيادة القدرة التنافسية للبنوك التجارية في مصر، في ظل تبنى القطاع المصرفي لإستراتيجية إطلاق المزيد من الخدمات المصرفية الإلكترونية، بغرض الوصول إلى أكبر قاعدة من العملاء وتعزيز الشمول المالي أحد البنود الهامة في رؤية مصر 2030، وقد تم التوصل من خلال الدراسة الميدانية إلى أن الاقتصاد الرقمي يحقق مزايا متعددة للبنوك والعملاء منها سهولة إجراء المعاملات، وخفض التكلفة المالية، كما تساهم رقمنه العمليات الداخلية في تقليل العمليات غير القانونية ومكافحة غسل الأموال وتقديم الخدمات المصرفية بأعلى مستوى من الكفاءة والجودة وبالتالي أرتفاع تنافسية البنوك، وتطبيق أحدث المعايير العالمية ، وتعظيم الناتج المحلى للاقتصاد المصري كما تم أقتراح مجموعة من التوصيات أهمها ضرورة رفع الوعى لدى العملاء في القطاع المصرفي لتغيير ثقافتهم في التعامل مع التطورات الحديثة في الخدمات المصرفية، وتنمية إمكانيات وخبرات العاملين لتتوافق مع التكنولوجيا الجديدة والتوسع في عدد شبكات فروع البنوك لتغطية كافة احتياجات العملاء.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; This research aims to identify the impact of the digital economy on increasing the competitiveness of commercial banks in egypt, In light of the adoption by the banking sector of the strategy of launching more electronic banking services, in order to reach the largest customer base and promote financial inclusion, one of the important items in Egypt's Vision 2030, It was concluded through the field study that the digital economy achieves multiple advantages for banks and customers, including ease of conducting transactions, reducing financial cost, and its digitation of internal processes contributes to reducing illegal operations, combating money laundering and providing banking services with the highest level of efficiency and quality and thus high competitiveness of banks, applying the latest international standards and maximizing the GDP of the Egyptian economy ,a series of recommendations have also been proposed, the most important of which is the need to raise awareness among customers in the banking sector to change their culture in dealing with recent developments in banking services, develop the capabilities and expertise of employees to conform to new technology and expand the number of bank branch networks to cover all customer needs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>التحديات التي تواجه القطاع الصناعي في مصر (دراسة واقع صناعة الأثاث في محافظة دمياط)</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285160.html</link>
      <description>&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; تمثل الهدف الرئيسي للبحث في دراسة طبيعة وواقع القطاع الصناعي في مصر والوقوف على أهم التحديات التي تواجه القطاع الصناعي في مصر، ودراسة طبيعة صناعة الأثاث في محافظة دمياط وأهم التحديات التي تواجه هذه الصناعة، بالتركيز على طبيعة محافظة دمياط وموقعها واهتمامها بصناعة الأثاث.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; واعتمدت الدراسة على المنهج الوصفي التحليلي بالاعتماد على البيانات المتاحة عن حجم القطاع الصناعي في مصر وكذلك عن صناعة الأثاث في محافظة دمياط وأهميتها التصديرية.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وتوصلت الدراسة إلى أن القطاع الصناعي في مصر يحتل مكانة هامة بين القطاعات الاقتصادية المختلفة في الاقتصاد المصري، حيث يساهم بما يقرب من ثلث الناتج المحلي الإجمالي، كما أنه يستحوذ على حوالي 28% من حجم العمالة في الاقتصاد المصري. كما توصلت الدراسة إلى أهمية قطاع صناعة الأثاث بمحافظة دمياط، حيث أن صادرات الأثاث الدمياطي تمثل ما يقرب من 24% من إجماليالصادرات المصرية خلال فترة الدراسة. والوقوف على أهم التحديات والصعوبات التي تواجه صناعة الأثاث في محافظة دمياط.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; وقد أوصت الدراسة بانتهاج استراتيجية من قبل الحكومة لتبني زراعة الأشجار التي تعتبر مصدر أساسي للمواد الخام اللازمة لصناعة الأثاث، وكذلك التوسع في إقامة المعارض والمشاركة في المعارض العالمية. والاهتمام بتنمية الصناعة في المكونات المحلية اللازمة لصناعة الأثاث.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The main objective of the research is to study the nature and reality of the industrial sector in Egypt and to identify the most important challenges facing the industrial sector in Egypt, and to study the nature of the furniture industry in Damietta Governorate and the most important challenges facing this industry, by focusing on the nature of Damietta Governorate, its location and its interest in the furniture industry.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study relied on the analytical descriptive approach based on the available data on the size of the industrial sector in Egypt, as well as on the furniture industry in Damietta Governorate and its export importance.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study concluded that the industrial sector in Egypt occupies an important position among the various economic sectors in the Egyptian economy, as it contributes nearly a third of the gross domestic product, and it also accounts for about 28% of the volume of employment in the Egyptian economy. The study also concluded the importance of the furniture industry sector in Damietta Governorate, as Damietta furniture exports represent approximately 24% of the total Egyptian exports during study time. And stand on the most important challenges and difficulties facing the furniture industry in Damietta Governorate.&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;amp;nbsp; The study recommended adopting a strategy by the government to adopt tree planting, which is an essential source of raw materials for the furniture industry, as well as expanding exhibitions and participating in international exhibitions. And interest in the development of the industry in the local components needed for the furniture industry.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>البعد الاجتماعي فى صناعة السياسات العامة فى مصر بالتطبيق على مفهوم النوع الاجتماعي</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_285136.html</link>
      <description>اصبح مفهوم النوع الاجتماعى والذى يعنى بالمساواة بين الجنسين الرجل والمرأه من اكثر المفاهيم شيوعا فى المحيط الدولى والذى بات يلزم الدول على صنع سياسات محليه مستجيبة لهذا التوجه العالمى.وتعد الخطة&amp;amp;nbsp; الاستثمارية هى الوثيقه الاهم فى توجيه استثمارات وسياسات الدوله نحو تنمية المجتمع&amp;amp;nbsp; والتى&amp;amp;nbsp; يتم تحديدها فى بنود الاتفاقيات الدوليه كمقياس لمؤشر استجابة الدول المتعاقدة لبنود المعاهدات والاتفاقيات وتختلف محاولات استجابة خطط التنمية لمفهوم النوع الاجتماعى وتتعدد في&amp;amp;nbsp; هذا الاطار التجارب الادارية حيث لم يتم تحديد اطار محدد للتطبيق فى تشكيل خطط التنمية&amp;amp;nbsp; ومدى قياس تطبيق المفهوم &amp;amp;nbsp;وتحاول الدراسة ادراك واقع استجابة الخطط التنموية لبنود المعاهدات الدوليه لمفهوم النوع الاجتماعى.&amp;amp;nbsp;The concept of gender, which means equality between the men and women, has become one of the most common concepts in the international environment, which obliges countries to make local policies responsive to this global trend.The investment plan is the most important document in directing the investments and policies of the state towards the development of society, which is specified in the provisions of international agreements as a measure of the indicator of the response of contracting countries to the provisions of treaties and agreements. Attempts to respond to development plans to the concept, and there are many administrative experiences in this context As no specific framework for application has been defined in the formation of development plans and the extent of measuring the application of the concept The study attempts to realize the reality of the response of development plans to the provisions of international treaties to the concept of gender.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>تاثير مشروع الحكومه الالكترونيه في الحكومه المصرية - خلال الفتره (2005_ 2020)</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280015.html</link>
      <description>يهدف البحث الى إستخدام وسائل التكنولوجيا الحديثة في إستخدام تقنية الحاسب الآلي والأخذ في الاعتبار إعداد الكوادر والقيادات البشرية لاستقبال خطوات تنفيذ مشاريع هذا النظام الحديث في مصر&amp;amp;nbsp; ومدى تطبيق مؤسسات الدولة لنظام الحكومة الإلكترونيةومن الضروري ملاحظة أن الحكومة الإلكترونية ليست بديلا أو اختصارا للتنمية الاقتصادية وتوفير الميزانية والحكومة الكفء، كما أنها ليست حدثا مفردا قد يتغير فورا وإلي الأبد الوضع الحكومي الراهن. فالحكومة الإلكترونية تمثل عملية، أو يمكن القول، أنها تطور أو غالبا صراع يعرض التكاليف والمخاطر المالية والسياسية.ومن الملاحظ، أن الحكومات العادية تلعب دورا قياديا هاما في تحسين المدى الذي يستفيد منه المواطنون ومنظمات الأعمال في المجتمع من خلال إتاحة الفرص التي تقدمها تكنولوجيا المعلومات والاتصالات المتقدمة للمساعدة في تحويل أنشطة الحكومة من الطرق والأساليب التقليدية ذات الطابع البيروقراطي إلي خدمات الحكومة الإلكترونية الديناميكية والتفاعلية، ولهذا التحول مظهر هام وتأثير قوي علي اجتياز كل المراحل الحرجة المرتبطة باقتصاد المعرفة الأوسع.The research aims to use the means of modern technology in the use of computer technology, and taking into account the preparation of human cadres and leaders to receive the steps of implementing the projects of this modern system in Egypt and the extent to which state institutions apply the e-government systemIt is necessary to note that e-government is not a substitute or a shortcut to economic development, budget provision and efficient government, nor is it a single event that may change immediately and forever the current government situation. E-government represents a process, or it can be said, that it develops or often a conflict that exposes costs and financial and political risks.It is noted that ordinary governments play an important leadership role in improving the extent to which citizens and business organizations benefit in society by providing opportunities provided by advanced information and communication technology to help transform government activities from traditional bureaucratic methods and methods to dynamic and interactive e-government services. This transformation has an important aspect and a strong impact on passing all the critical stages associated with the broader knowledge economy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>مسار العلاقات المصرية – السودانية وآثار التقسيم</title>
      <link>https://jces.journals.ekb.eg/article_280019.html</link>
      <description>اصبح الامن القومي المصري والسوداني يواجهان تهديدات كثير خاصة وأن انفصال جنوب السودان عن السودان هو بمثابة تحدي حقيقي للسودان ويرجع ذلك لفقدها أكثر من ثلث مساحتها بالإضافة الي ثروات ضخمة تتمتع&amp;amp;nbsp; بها منطقة جنوب السودان وكل هذا سيترك اثر كبير علي السودان والمنطقة بأثرها ، وأن موقع مصر الجغرافي الذي جعلها في قلب التفاعلات وعلي الرغم من أن حدود جنوب السودان والحدود المصرية ليست علي ملامسة او تماس لكن مصر عرضة للتأثر بالأوضاع المستجدة في جنوب السودان .عقب قيام ثورة يناير 2011 مباشرة كان هدف القيادة السياسية المصرية المؤقتة تدعيم العلاقات المصرية مع دول العالم اجمع وخاصة السودان لما لها من اهمية كبيرة للدولة المصرية فقد ظهر ذلك في اهتمام القيادة المصرية بعمل زيارات مكثفة للسودان بهدف بحث كافة سبل التعاون بين البلدين وبالفعل ازدهرت العلاقات الثنائية في تلك الفترة&amp;amp;nbsp; مقارنة بالفترة السابقة ، وبعد تولي الرئيس المصري / عبدالفتاح السيسي منصب رئاسة الجمهورية حدث ازدهار في العلاقات المصرية السودانية وكان ذلك بسبب النهج الذي تبناه الرئيس عبدالفتاح السيسي تجاه السودان وتأكيد سيادته علي اهمية دعم الروابط الازلية والاستراتيجية بين البلدين مع ضرورة تجاوز اي خلافات سابقة بين البلدين .Egyptian and Sudanese national security have become facing many threats, especially since the secession of South Sudan from Sudan is a real challenge to Sudan due to the loss of more than a third of its area in addition to the huge wealth enjoyed by the South Sudan region and all this will leave a great impact on Sudan and the region with its impact, and that Egypt's geographical location that made it at the heart of interactions and although the borders of South Sudan and the Egyptian border are not in contact or contact, but Egypt is vulnerable to being affected by the new situations In South Sudan.Immediately after the January 2011 revolution, the goal of the interim Egyptian political leadership was to strengthen Egyptian relations with the countries of the whole world, especially Sudan, because of its great importance to the Egyptian state, as this was reflected in the interest of the Egyptian leadership in making intensive visits to Sudan in order to discuss all means of cooperation between the two countries, and indeed bilateral relations flourished in that period compared to the previous period, After the assumption of the post of President of the Republic by Egyptian President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi, there was a boom in Egyptian-Sudanese relations due to the approach adopted by President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi towards Sudan and his sovereignty stressed the importance of supporting the eternal and strategic ties between the two countries with the need to overcome any previous differences between the two countries.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
